<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-06T16:15+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Produced by GROBID</resp>
					<name resp="ISTEX-API">ISTEX-API (INIST-CNRS)</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>PS.-ALBERT T H E G R E A T ON T H E PHYSIOGNOMY OF JESUS AND MARY* Irv e n M . R e sn ic k</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>A R L Y C h ristianity produced several literary accou n ts to support sp e c ific icon ograp h ic d ep iction s o f J esu s, M ary, and th e sa in ts, w h ich seek u lti­ m ately to esta b lish th at one can state au th oritatively w h at each on e actu ally look ed lik e. F or exam ple, th e legendary v e il o f V eron ica pretends to o ffer a true im age o f J esu s&apos;s v isa g e th at had b een transferred to her clo th as Jesus w ip ed h is fa c e on th e road to C alvary.1 S im ilarly, th e legend o f A b gar o f E d essa p rovid es b oth a literary and icon ograp hic b a sis for a d escrip tion o f J e su s&apos; p h y sica l appearance. A ccord in g to one version o f th e p rob ably third-century legen d o f A bgar, H anan, A b gar&apos;s arch ivist and painter, had b een charged to p ain t a portrait o f Jesu s. W hen h e com pleted h is ta sk h e brought th e h o ly im age b ack w ith him to E d essa, w here it becam e an ob ject o f ven ­ eration.2 In an alternative accou n t, Jesus provided A b gar w ith a self-p ortrait.3 S im ilarly, th e a p o stle Luke is sa id to h ave painted an auth oritative im age o f th e V irg in M ary, w h ich w a s then le ft to th e Church. L ater B yzan tin e th eo ­ lo g ia n s com m only affirm ed th e au th en ticity o f b oth th e portrait o f Jesu s sent to A b gar o f E d essa and L uke&apos;s portrait o f M ary.4 A p ictu re o f th e V irgin in R om e&apos;s S. M aria M aggiore is ascrib ed to Luke. * I would like to express my gratitude to the National Endowment for the Humanities for financial support that enabled me to begin work on this paper, and, to the Oxford Centre for Hebrew and Jewish Studies, which kindly opened its facilities to me as a visiting scholar during the summer months o f 2000. 1 One version o f the legend o f Veronica&apos;s veil can be found, for example, in the apocryphal D ea th o f P ila te (M ors P ila ti). In this work, as in the legend o f Abgar o f Edessa, the image o f Jesus has a miraculous healing power. For the history o f the image, see Ewa Kuryluk, Veronica a n d H e r C loth : H istory, S ym bolism , a n d Stru ctu re o f a &quot;True&quot; Im age (Cambridge, M ass., 1991). 1 The T eaching o f A d d a i, trans. George Howard, Early Christian Literature Series 4 , Texts and Translations 16 (Chico, Ca., 1981), 9. For this Syriac text and tradition, see also the H is­ to ire du ro i A b g a r e t d e Jésus, ed. Alain Desreumaux, Apocryphes 3 (Tumhout, 1993). 3 Another version o f the legendary correspondance between Abgar and Jesus, although without reference to the portrait, is found in Eusebius o f Caesarea&apos;s H isto ria e c clesia stica 1.13. 4 See, for example, chap. 69 o f Theodore the Studite&apos;s v ita (PG 99:178D). M ediaeval Studies 64 (2002): 217-40. © Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies. PS.-ALBERT THE GREAT ON THE PHYSIOGNOMY OF JESUS AND MARY 2 1 9 and to A risto tle. T he A ristotelian , or rather p seu d o-A ristotelian m aterials, in ­ clu d e the Secretum secretorum-introduced to th e cou rt o f Frederick II in the lon g form translated b y P h ilip o f T rip oli9-and P s.-A r isto tle &apos;s Physiognomy, translated b y B artholom ew o f M essin a som etim e b efore 1 2 6 2 , alth ough a draft or ou tlin e o f th e w ork seem s to h ave b een a v a ila b le ea rlier.10 T h ese w ork s, a s w e ll a s A rab ic sou rces th at transm itted th eir d octrin es, p resented to th e L atin w orld th e p h ysiogn om y o f th e an cien ts. M o st im portant, it w a s in th e thirteenth century that p h ysiogn om y a s a s c i­ en ce w a s seen a s a proper instrum ent fo r d iscerning in th e outw ard appear­ an ce o f a hum an (or anim al) th e accid en tal properties o f th e so u l. In other w ords, th e extern al appearance, w h en properly interpreted, b ecam e a m irror o f th e inner b ein g and cou ld reveal its natu re.11 It is n o t coin cid en tal, th en , th at M ich a el S co t, translator o f A risto tle&apos;s H istoria animalium, le ft u s a lso a L iber phisionom iae-better know n in th e R en aissan ce under th e title D e secretis nature. T h is L iber phisionom iae con stitu tes th e third b ook o f h is tripartite L iber introductorius, and fo llo w s after th e L iber quattuor distinctionum and L iber particularis. It has b een d escrib ed as th e fir st true w ork on p h y sio g ­ nom y com p osed in th e m ed ieval W e st.12 D ed icated to Frederick II, M ich ael</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>R eg a rd less o f th eir au th en ticity, th ese legen d s w ou ld esta b lish an authorita­ tiv e b a sis fo r venerated d ep iction s o f Jesus and M ary b y arguing for th eir a p o sto lic origin . In th e a b sen ce o f tradition s for a p o sto lic ity , claim s o f m ira cu lo u sly produced im ages (acheiropoietai) o f th e sain ts serve th e sam e p u rp o se.5 W h ereas legen d s su ch as th ese provided to churchm en from la te an­ tiq u ity and th e early M iddle A g e s a foundation from w h ich to fa sh io n im ages o f J esu s, M ary, and th e sa in ts, th eir role w a s, in at lea st one sch o la stic te x t from th e thirteenth century, usurped b y a d iscu ssio n rooted in physiogn om y. P h y sio g n o m y w ill provide an opportunity to fash ion d ep iction s o f Jesu s and M ary on an a lleg ed ly scientific b a sis. In th e fo llo w in g , I intend to exam in e a p ortion o f on e sch o la stic te x t, P s.-A lb ert th e G reat's M ariale or CCXXX quaestiones super Evangelium "M issus e s t" {quaestiones 1 7 -2 0 ), a s a sort o f c a se stu d y o f th e im pact o f p h ysiogn om y on th eology.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. P h y s io g n o m y a s S c ie n c e in t h e T h ir t e e n t h C e n t u r y A s in d icated ab ove, although th ese icon ograp hic legend s and others re­ m ained p opu lar in m ed ieval L atin C hristendom ,6 it fe ll to thirteenth-century sc h o la stics to attem pt a scientific accou n t o f th e p h y sica l appearance o f Jesus</head><p>and M ary. T h e p o ssib ility o f su ch an accou n t depended first on th e introduc­ tio n o f a n cien t G reek m ed ical te x ts and tr ea tises on p hysiogn om y. A lth ou gh a fe w p re-sch o la stic authors reveal som e acquaintance w ith p h ysiogn om y, a gen u in e in terest in and system atic accou n t o f p h ysiogn om y is en tirely ab sen t am ong th em . <ref type="bibr" coords="2,122.93,400.06,3.50,8.55">7</ref>  11 For this theme, see especially Jole Agrimi, "Fisiognomica: nature alio specchio ow ero luce e ombre," M ic ro lo g u s 4: II teatro d e lla natura <ref type="bibr" coords="3,232.50,570.52,61.25,7.20">(Tumhout, 1996)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" coords="3,301.15,570.52,28.00,7.20">129-78.</ref> 12 See D anielle Jacquart, "La Physiognomonie à l 'époque de Frédéric K: Le traité de M ichel Scot," 20. M ichael's authorship o f the L ib e r ph isio n o m ia e or, in general, o f the L ib e r in trodu ctoriu s, seems w ell established but Charles Burnett, noting the extensive use Bartholo-S c o t com p osed th e w ork to en ab le th e em peror to d istin gu ish , from outw ard appearan ces, trustw orth y and w ise cou n selors from th eir op p osite num bers. S u ch a scien ce is so u sefu l to a ruler th at M ichael S co t d oes n ot h esita te to de­ scrib e it a s a "doctrine o f sa lv a tio n ."13 N o r is it coin cid en tal th at A lb ert the G  W hen the nostrils are sharp at the tip, they indicate a person quick to anger. W hen they are inordinately thick, they announce that the person is to be thought o f as foul. When the bottoms o f the nostrils are solid and round, blunt as it were, they declare him strong and great-hearted. Plato felt that such nos­ trils were given to leonine and well-born "canine" men. This is because he saw such nostrils on lion s and well-born dogs and he said that a certain likeness exists between various anim als and men and that people im itate the habits o f such anim als.24 P la to 's (m ore p rob ably, P alem on 's) ob servation th at th is ty p e o f n ostril ty p ic a lly appeared in on ly w ell-b orn or n ob le an im als, and th at a certain a n a lo g y e x is ts b etw een hum ans and an im als, lead s to th e co n clu sio n th at in hum ans to o "the n o strils <ref type="bibr" coords="6,186.74,398.61,22.51,8.55">[that]</ref>    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>reat d evoted tw o q uestions to a d efen se o f p h ysiogn om y in h is Quaestiones super de anim alibus,14 or th at a large sectio n o f th e first b ook o f h is D e animalibus is g iv e n over to th e stu dy o f p h ysiogn om y, som etim es circu latin g independently under th e title D e physiognomic*.15 A b ou t th e tim e o f th e com ­ p o sitio n o f D e animalibus-ca. 1263-p h ysiogn om y w a s becom in g w e ll in te­ grated into th e stu dy o f scien ce and natural p h ilosop h y in m ed ieval E urope.16 A lb ert, in particu lar, d evotes th e second chapter o f th e first b ook o f h is D e animalibus to th e "scien ce o f p h ysiogn om y." There h e p rop oses to reveal h ow "p h ysiogn om y . . . tea ch es one to m ake pred iction s ab ou t hum an d isp o sitio n s u sin g th e p h y sica l sh apes o f th eir m em bers." 17 A m ong hum an b ein g s, then, m ew o f Parma made o f M ichael's work, has suggested that Bartholomew edited M ichael's L ib e r p a rtic u la ris and L ib e r q u a ttu o r distinctionum . Therefore, he warns, "great caution must be exercised in accrediting anything in the L ib e r in trodu ctoriu s to M ichael." See Charles Bur­ nett, "Michael Scot and the Transmission o f Scientific Culture from Toledo to Bologna via the</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>certain pred ictab le form s o f beh avior arise from our p h y sica l con stitu tion s: from th e hum oral com p lexion and th e form or arrangem ent o f our m em bers. T h is is n o t to sa y th at w e are pre-determ ined to act in a certain w a y at birth b ut o n ly th a t sin ce th e so u l is u nited to th e b ody, th e b od y can a ffe c t th e so u l, ju s t a s th e rational so u l, w hen properly develop ed , can (and ou ght to ) govern th e d esires and in clin ation s o f th e body. T o th e exten t th at our b eh avior can b e traced b a ck to a rational w ill, A lbert w ill d iscu ss it in h is com m entary on A r isto tle's Nicomachean Ethics; to th e exten t that it is a ffected and revealed b y th e b od y, h e w ill d isc u ss it under th e scien ce o f p hysiogn om y. A lb ert's nam ed au th orities in th e d isc u ssio n o f th is scien ce are A risto tle (or P s.-A r isto tle), A vicen n a, C onstantine th e A frica n ,18 L e x u s, and P alem on .19 T h ese, a s w e ll a s a fe w authors on ju d ic ia l astrology-sin ce th e stars m ay a lso a ffe c t th e d isp o sitio n o f th e m atter w hen th e b od y is form ed-p rovide A lb ert w ith th e p rin cip les o f a scien ce o f p hysiogn om y. A lth ou gh p h ysiogn om y m ay exam ine a ll o f th e m em bers o f th e b od y to de­ term ine th e in clin ation s or p a ssio n s o f th e sou l-i.e ., th e character o f th e ind i­ v id u al-it is th e fa c e and th o se organs nearest th e brain th at h ave an esp e c ia lly ex a lted p la c e for th e p h ysiogn om ist.20 H igh est am ong them w ill b e th e ey es. A lb ert remarks th at "T he entire p erfection o f p h ysiogn om y ex ists in th e ey es. F or P alem on sa y s th ey are lik e th e 'flow ers o f th e s o u l,' th at th e so u l sh in es forth through th e eyes and th at th eir so le d isp o sitio n is to b e an en­</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>O nce a gain , in iso la tio n th ese p h y sica l indicators m ight n ot provide u sefu l inform ation to th e p h ysiogn om ist, b ut th e accum ulated w eigh t o f evid en ceb a sed on th e form ation o f m any o f th e m em bers o f th e body-w a s accep ted as h a v in g p rob ative v alu e. C onsequently, th e m od em reader m u st b ear p atien tly</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>in p articu lar a s h avin g a pure and w ell-b alan ced com p lexion .27 In a sim ilar w a y M ich a el S co t d istin gu ish es th e p h y sica l featu res o f p eop les in d ifferen t g eo g ra p h ica l regions:</head><p>In warm regions the native peoples (gentes) have brown skin, as is evident am ong the E th iop ian s.. . . They have dry curly hair and they have hair that is coarse and rough. But in cold regions tall people are bom and they have a very pale or w hite skin. They are denuded o f hair or alm ost so, especially those who are very pale or white. Note too that a region varies by province and, with respect to a woman's womb, i f both are warm, then the creature generated w ill be warm and the one generated w ill be black or brown, etc. But i f both are cold, then [the creature] w ill be more or less w hite according to the com­ plexion o f the region.28 The physiognom y o f the skin is assigned by the w ise man Phylemon, who says that a soft, dark color indicates a clever, tim id person and refers to those who liv e in the first four climata. A fair, pink color, however, indicates brave, spir­ ited people, and this is especially a trait o f those liv in g in Germany and in ­ habitants o f the sixth and seventh climata.31 The clim ata are the longitudinal bands into which medieval geographers divided the world. For Albert, there are seven clim ata, divided according to differences in longitude and latitude. For each clim a there w ill be a balanced complexion appropriate to it, so much so that "a Dacian who nears balance o f complexion for his habitation would quickly die in India or Ethiopia, and it is the same for other differences in clim a " ("Dacus autem attingens aequale complexionis suae habitationis cito moreretur in India vel Ethiopia, et sic est de aliis climatum differentiis," ibid. 12.1.4.59; On A nim als, 915). th e g en era lly recogn ized ch aracteristics and tem peram ents o f grou p s. A s a p ra ctica l scien ce , it cou ld provide u sefu l inform ation both ab ou t ind ividu als and races. From extern al appearances, th e p h ysiogn om ist m ight infer a great d eal ab ou t m oral character, m ental a b ilitie s, and th e p a ssio n a l nature. M ichael S co t certain ly b eliev ed th at th is scien ce w ou ld p rove e sp ec ia lly u sefu l at cou rt, a s rulers sou gh t to id en tify trustw orthy and w ise cou n selors.  <ref type="figure" coords="11,44.66,127.41,346.32,8.55;11,44.66,140.41,345.68,8.55;11,44.66,153.11,346.29,8.55;11,45.11,165.81,25.24,8.55">from extern al sig n s, b eca u se a person is m ore in clin ed to one sin than another  a ccord in g to variou s com p lexion s. I f h e is a ch oleric h e is m ore in clin ed to  w rath, b ut i f a m elan ch olic he is m ore in clin ed to en m ity."35 For th is reason , it  seem s</ref>   <ref type="figure" coords="12,59.30,121.91,345.76,8.55;12,59.50,134.86,297.61,8.55">g e lic and anim al natures-sh ould approach th at o f ce lestia l b od ies. C on se­  q uently, rem arks A lb ert th e G reat, "m an, am ong a ll creatures, m</ref>   42 "Christ had the best complexion, which clearly is owing to the fact that he had the most noble soul, to which a balanced complexion corresponds in the body" ("Christus fuit optime complexionatus: quod patet ex eo quod habuit nobilissimam animam, cui respondet aequalitas complexionis in corpore," Thomas Aquinas, In III Sent. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>From th is it is clear that th e b od y and its appearance is a ffected b y con d ition s o f th e w om b and, later, b y clim ate and geograph y. A lb ert th e G reat p rovid es another w itn ess and n otes th at "H air a lso d iffers accord ing to th e di­ v er sity o f reg ion s, fo r d iversity o f d w elling p la c e a lso ca u ses d iversity o f co m p lex io n , even am ong th o se liv in g in them . For th e hair o f m en w h o are in w arm p la c es is hard and cu rly, as is th e h air o f th e E th iopians. B u t th e hair o f th o se in co ld p la ces is s o ft."29 A lb ert's rem arks, lik e th o se o f M ichael S co t, are n ot m erely intended to reflect ob servab le d ifferen ces am ong races or p eo p les in d ifferen t parts o f th e w orld, b u t a lso to su g g est an accom p anyin g character appropriate to each. T hu s, 27 P o lem o n is d e ph ysio g n o m o n ia lib e r 35, ed. G. Hoffmann in Foerster, S crip to res</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In a v ery real sen se, then, p h ysiogn om y w as linked to several d iscip lin es: to zo o lo g y , fo r its d iscu ssio n o f anim als and th eir ch aracteristics and tem pera­ m ents; to m edicin e and anatom y, fo r its d iscu ssio n o f th e hum an b od y and its</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B y th e fourteenth century th e cla im s o f p h ysiogn om ists m u st a lso h ave ach ieved a w id e popu lar accep tan ce, as evid en ced b y C haucer's u se in sk etch in g th e p ilgrim s in th e Canterbury Tales.3,2 From th e p h y sica l d escrip ­ tio n s o f th e Pardoner or th e R eeve, C haucer's readers w ou ld certain ly h ave deduced th e m ost im portant featu res o f th eir character. Y et, popu lar fam iliar­ ity w ith th e con ven tion s o f p h ysiogn om y lik e ly did n ot stem from w id esp read acq u ain tan ce w ith sch o la stic w orks o f natural scien ce but from th eir ap p lica­ tio n in p astoral or ordinary relig io u s con texts. For p hysiogn om y to acquire a fo o th o ld in relig io u s d iscou rse, it had first to p rove its va lu e to th eologian s.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. P h y s io g n o m y a n d S c h o l a s t ic T h e o l o g y B y th e thirteenth-century, th eologian s had put to go o d u se inform ation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F or p ra ctica l theology, A lan o f L ille ( f 1 2 0 2 /3 ) su g g ests th at in d ivid u als m ay b e m ore in clin ed to sp e c ific sin s b ecau se o f th eir hum oral com p lexion . T hu s, "the sin n er's com p lexion m u st b e considered, in sofar a s it can b e exam ined</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>iv e s exp ression to a tradition th at h eld th at w h en still in P arad ise, A d am 's com p lexion "w a s p erfectly tem perate, as h e had equal shares o f th e fou r q u a lities." A s a resu lt o f h is sin and d isob ed ien ce, h ow ever, A dam 's d escendants h ave departed from a p erfectly b alan ced tem perate com ­ p le x io n and th e hum an b od y su bseq u en tly su ffered corruption. A fter A dam w a s driven ou t o f Eden, "h is b od y b egan to dry out . . . [and] h is natural h eat</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G od g a v e to hum ans th e m ost n oble, b alanced com plexion 39 4 0 and, in general term s, th e id eal hum an com plexion -g iv en our sem inal p o sitio n b etw een an­</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>est and m o st b alan ced hum an com p lexion both b ecau se h is so u l w as m o st p erfect and b eca u se h is b od y w a s fash ion ed n o t in th e norm al w a y , b ut m iracu lou sly b y th e H o ly S pirit.42 S im ilarly A lb ert th e G reat, fo llo w in g P lato, affirm s th at "the m o st n o b le so u l is ow ed to th e m ost b alanced com p lexion " b eca u se each com p lexion receiv es a form proper to it,43 and S t. B onaventure co n firms that J esu s's b o d y d isp layed th e b est p o ssib le com p lexion .44</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>15.2.3, ed. P. Mandoimet and M. F. M oos, S criptu m su p er lib ro s Sententiarum , 4 vols. [Paris, 1929-47], 3:495). See also</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="47">A lo n g w ith th e q u estion o f authorship, th e date o f th e w ork rem ains in d isp u te, w ith su g g esio n s ranging from 1 2 4 0 to 13 0 0 . N everth eless, stu d ies o f its literary in fluence48 and m anu­ scrip t tran sm ission 49 in d icate th at it circu lated and w a s cop ied fa irly often. T he sig n ifica n ce o f th is te x t fo r a d iscu ssio n o f p hysiogn om y, it seem s to m e, is tw ofold : 1) perhaps for th e fir st tim e it attem pts to articulate fu lly the im p lica tio n s o f th e n otion th at th e b od y o f M ary (and Jesus as w e ll) w ill re­ v e a l th e b e st hum an com plexion ; 2 ) in doing so , it puts real fle sh , so to speak, on M arian b ones and refu ses to treat M ary m erely as a th eo lo g ica l sym b ol and a cou n terw eigh t to E ve. M ary becom es a h istorical p erson , fo r w hom th e s c i­ en ce o f p h ysign om y can p rovide a su itab le v isa g e .50</head><p>tenerior, tanto eins poena dolorosior" (Bonaventure, Serm ones dom in icales 14.12, ed. J. G. Bougerai <ref type="bibr" coords="13,77.73,362.68,74.08,7.20">[Grottaferrata, 1977]</ref>    <ref type="figure" coords="14,295.72,599.82,109.88,7.20;14,59.74,609.87,40.92,7.20">: ergo, etc." (ibid. 18.11, ed.  Borgnet, 43</ref>). <ref type="figure" coords="15,42.25,114.96,322.80,8.55">in d icate th at th e m ost b eau tifu l ey es w ill h ave color (i.e ., b lu e, or grey,</ref>     <ref type="figure" coords="15,139.87,550.12,248.68,7.20;15,42.67,560.22,260.27,7.20">Et hoc modo capilli talis cerebri in infantibus sunt subfulvi, in pueris  vero subflavi, in perfectis vero flavi . ..." (ibid. 20.3, ed. Borgnet, 46)</ref>. Albert identifies four functions specific to the <ref type="figure" coords="15,137.30,570.77,250.67,7.20;15,43.42,581.07,83.58,7.20">natural virtu s: attraction, digestion, retention, and expulsion (ibid.  12.5, ed. Borgnet, 227)</ref>. Note, however, that Albert recognizes only three principal members: the brain, heart, and liver; see D e a n im alibu s 1.1.5.73 <ref type="figure" coords="15,243.07,590.92,61.68,7.20">(O n A nim als, 72)</ref>. 60 "Alio modo dicitur eucraticum cerebrum, secundum quod est optime dispositum et ordi- <ref type="figure" coords="16,59.75,124.06,346.67,8.55;16,59.50,137.26,346.61,8.55;16,59.75,150.21,346.89,8.55;16,59.75,162.96,346.66,8.55;16,60.00,175.91,346.13,8.55;16,60.25,188.86,345.89,8.55;16,60.25,201.61,346.25,8.55;16,60.00,214.81,346.36,8.55;16,60.25,227.51,292.82,8.55">virtutes: th e natural, th e v ita l or sp iritual, and th e an im al.61 F or C onstantine  th e A frica n , th e natural sp irit a rises in th e liv er and tra v els through th e v ein s  to adm inister th e natural fa cu lty , regulating th e fu n ction s o f th e p rincipal  m em bers o f th e body; a v ita l sp irit a rises in th e heart and travels through the  arteries to adm inister th e v ita l facu lty; th e anim al sp irit a rises in th e v en tricles  o f th e b rain, tra v els through th e n erves, and adm inisters th e anim al fa c u lty ,  regulatin g va riou s fu n ction s o f th e sou l. C harles B urnett h as n oted th at for  b oth C onstantine th e A frica n 's Pantegni and h is principal A rabic sou rce, the  anim al sp irit is a d ecocted product o f th e h eart's v ita l sp irit, p u</ref>   <ref type="figure" coords="17,96.95,127.66,291.07,8.55;17,42.25,140.61,346.31,8.55;17,42.25,153.61,190.66,8.55">d isp atched to th e particular sen ses. . . ."63 It is then th e anim al  sp irit's corresponding virtus, the anim al fa cu lty , th at is linked to th e a ct o f  co g n itio n and th e operations o f th e in tellect.</ref>  <ref type="figure" coords="17,155.18,436.13,210.61,7.20">, Q uaestion es su p er d e an im alibu s 12.17, ed. Filthaut, 235</ref>). For Albert, the brain must be cold relative to the heart to temper the heart's dynamic heat: "Quod probatur, quia cerebrum hominis est magis frigidum et humidum, et hoc, ut obtemperet calorem cordis . <ref type="figure" coords="17,71.74,467.08,316.18,7.20;17,42.24,477.63,345.92,7.20;17,42.24,488.23,230.81,7.20">. ." (ibid. 1.34-37, ed. Filthaut, 101.33-34). When its coldness causes the condensation  o f the moist vapors rising to the brain, this condensation blocks the operation o f the animal  virtues and brings on sleep (ibid. 4.11, ed. Filthaut, 146.23-28)</ref>. 68 For the claim that chastity naturally demands a cold complexion, suggesting therefore that the Virgin must have had a very cold complexion, see M a ria le 18.6-8; for the arguments to the contrary, see q. 18.9-11. However, at q. 20.3 (p. 45), Ps.-Albert responds that since the Vir­ gin's chastity is a product o f grace and not nature, her complexion must be understood to be warm, and not cold (see n. 75 below). The argument that chastity is more natural in a cold complexion, whereas sexual desire arises from a warmer nature, w ill be found too in Michael Scot's L ib e r p h isio n o m ia e 4 -5 <ref type="bibr" coords="18,177.81,476.23,13.28,7.20">(27)</ref>  <ref type="figure" coords="22,80.17,148.31,326.66,8.55;22,60.71,161.01,325.01,8.55">o f v ic e s. F or M ichael S co t, red h air sig n ifie s a person w h o is en viou s,  v en a l, d u p licito u s, proud, and ill-sp ea k in g .88 In creasin gly, red hair w a s</ref>   <ref type="figure" coords="22,151.44,610.12,143.38,7.20">an im alibu s 19.3.12 {On A nim als, 1338)</ref>, that black eyes result from an from a d eficien cy in th e crystallin e hum or, our author rem arks th at th ough th e p a u city o f th e hum or is th e cau se o f th e b lack color in th e ey e, it is n ot a d efi­ cien cy . R ather, it reflects th e fa c t th at a n ob le brain-w arm and dry-requires o n ly a purer and m ore su b tle nutrim ent, and therefore d oes n ot n eed m ore o f th e cry sta llin e hum or to su stain th e e y e s' v isio n . In con clu sio n , </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="46">See Franz Pelster, K ritisch e Studien zum L eben und zu den Schriften A lb e rts des G rossen (Freiburg im Breisgau, 1920), 109-12; and Meersseman, In trodu ctio in op era om nia B . A lb e rti M a g n i O .P., 119-20. 47 See Albert Fries, D ie unter dem N am en d e s A lb ertu s M agn u s überlieferten M a rio lo ­ gisch en Schriften. L itera rk ritisch e U ntersuchung, Beiträge zur Geschichte der Philosophie und Theologie des Mittelalters 37/4 (Münster, 1954), 5-80; Bruno Korosak, M a rio lo g ia S. A lb e rti M a g n i eiusque coaequalium . Bibliotheca Mariana M edii Aevi, Textus et Disquisitiones 8 (Rome, 1954), 3-18; and Franz Pelster, "Z wei Untersuchungen über die literarischen Grundla­ gen für die Darstellung einer Mariologie des hl. Alberts des Großen," S ch o la stik 30 (1955): 388-402. Their arguments are reviewed by A. Kolping, "Zur Frage des Textgeschichte, Herkunft und Entstehungszeit der anonymen L au s Virginis (bisher M a ria le Alberts des Großen)," R ech erch es d e th éologie ancienne e t m é diévale 25 (1958): 285-328. N o one has as</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In quaestiones 1 7 -2 0 in particular th e author p uts on d isp lay h is know ledge o f p h ysiogn om y and attem pts to recon cile discordant m edical au th oritiesesp e c ia lly G alen and C onstantine th e A frican -w h o se co n flictin g testim on y w o u ld lea d to quite d ifferen t portraits o f th e V irgin and her Son. F ollow in g G alen, th e p h y siogn om ist w ill con clu de th at M ary (and, b y in ference, Jesu s) had red hair, sin ce red hair is appropriate to a b od y w h ose hum oral com ­ p lex io n is w e ll b alanced;51 fo llo w in g C onstantine th e A frican , one m u st con ­ clu de th a t it w a s b la ck .52 F o llo w in g A risto tle, one w ou ld con clu d e th at the V irg in 's sk in had to b e w h ite, sin ce am ong colors th e sim p le extrem es-w h ite and b la ck -are m o st p erfect and, sin ce w h iten ess reflects th e ca u sa l e ffic a c y o f lig h t b etter than b la ck n ess, a w h ite b od y w ill b e m ore p erfect than b la ck .53 S om e co n clu d e th at her skin sh ould b e ruddy in co lo r, sin ce th is reflects a san guin e co m p lex io n ,54 w h ile others im p ly th at her skin sh ould b e b lack to</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F or a determ ination regarding her ey e s, our author n otes th at som e h ave ar­ gu ed th at w hen th e h air is b lack , ty p ica lly the ey e and h air co lo r agree. O thers</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>estcom p lexion ed brain w ill b e w arm and m oist and w ill, th erefore, b e indicated b y th e appropriate hair co lo r (reddish y e llo w for infants; lig h t blon d for ado­ lescen ts; and g o ld or fla x en for a d u lts).59 In th e second , w hen ordered to the anim al fa c u lty w h ich , in conjunction w ith th e anim al sp irit, is essen tia l to th e p ro cess o f co gn ition , th e brain w ill b e h ot and dry b eca u se th is is th e com ­ p le x io n b e st su ited to cogn ition .60</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>o o k o f the Ten T reatises on the E ye (K ita b a l-'a s h r M a k a la tfi' l-'a in ) is also attributed to him. On the Isa g o g e and its manuscript tradition, see Francis Newton, "Constantine the African and Monte Cassino: N ew Elements and the Text o f the I s a g o g e in C onstantine the A frican a n d ' A ll ibn a l -'A b b a s a l M agiisi. The P an tegn i a n d R e la te d Texts, ed. Charles Burnett and</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T h is a llu sio n to th e natural and anim al fa cu lties draw s u pon th e w e ll estab ­ lish ed m ed ica l tradition o f th e three sp irits and th eir corresponding fa c u ltie s or</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0" coords="2,130.28,400.06,278.63,8.55;2,63.08,413.01,348.43,8.55;2,77.73,444.28,331.69,7.20;2,62.87,454.83,234.17,7.20;2,77.72,465.43,331.66,7.20;2,62.87,475.73,346.62,7.20;2,63.33,486.28,346.02,7.20;2,62.88,496.63,346.62,7.20;2,62.88,506.93,345.38,7.20;2,63.34,517.03,124.36,7.20;2,77.74,527.58,330.64,7.20;2,62.13,537.88,346.67,7.20;2,62.88,548.43,346.37,7.20;2,62.38,558.53,347.01,7.20;2,62.63,568.83,346.92,7.20;2,62.88,579.18,346.37,7.20;2,62.88,589.47,345.54,7.20;2,62.88,599.32,86.50,7.20;2,77.28,609.87,332.16,7.20;3,41.28,341.58,347.35,7.20;3,41.98,351.88,345.99,7.20;3,41.48,362.43,241.79,7.20;3,59.28,373.03,330.32,7.20;3,41.72,383.33,346.96,7.20;3,41.97,393.88,346.09,7.20;3,42.22,404.43,346.45,7.20;3,42.21,415.03,345.83,7.20;3,41.96,425.33,201.48,7.20;3,57.06,435.88,331.49,7.20;3,41.46,446.23,346.39,7.20;3,42.46,456.53,346.13,7.20;3,41.96,466.83,345.65,7.20;3,41.96,477.18,346.71,7.20;3,41.96,487.73,346.51,7.20;3,41.96,498.03,346.53,7.20;3,41.46,508.38,346.83,7.20;3,42.21,518.93,345.68,7.20;3,42.21,529.48,345.95,7.20;3,41.96,539.83,346.22,7.20;3,41.70,549.88,218.50,7.20"><head>F or th e sc h o la stics, th e m ost in flu en tial trea tises on p h y sio g ­ nom y w ere th o se attributed erron eou sly to P lato (or other an cien t w o r th ie s), 8 5. 6 For example, Albert the Great mentions (following Eusebius o f Caesarea) that the woman who was healed by Jesus o f a bloody flux (cf. Luke 8: 43 f.) "had an image made in the likeness o f the Saviour" ("ad similitudinem Salvatoris fecit fieri imaginem"), dressed it in garments like those he wore, and placed it in her garden. Any herb that grew under the image also enjoyed the power to cure this bloody flux.-B). John o f Salisbury also mentions the teaching o f the physiog­ nomists (which John knew from Pliny the Elder's N a tu ra lis H isto ria ) but only in passing. See P o lic ra tic u s 5 . 15 , ed. C. C. J. Webb, 2 vols. (Oxford, 1909 ), 1 : 345 . Nevertheless, physiognomy w as popular among Roman authors and its principles were certainly known to some early Christian writers. For discussion, see Elizabeth C. Evans, "The Study o f Physiognomy in the Second Century A .D .," T ran saction s a n d P ro ceed in g s o f the A m erican P h ilo lo g ic a l A sso c ia ­ tion 72 ( 1941 ): 96 - 108 . 8 For a collection o f such treatises, see especially S c rip to re s ph ysio g n o m o n ici G ra eci e t L atin i, ed. R. Foerster, 2 vols. (Leipzig, 1893 ; rpt. Stuttgart and Leipzig, 1994 ). For the very popular anonymous treatise D e p h ysiogn om on ia lib e r with a French translation, see A nonym e L a tin T raité d e ph ysiogn om ie, trans. Jacques André (Paris, 1981 ). 9 For a brief summary, see W illiam Eamon's. For the claim that Michael Scot used Philip o f Tripoli's translation at Frederick IPs court, see Steven J.. Ps.-Aristotle's text on physiognomy was frequently commented on. For a discussion o f John Buridan's fourteenth-century commentary, see Lynn Thorndike, "Buridan's Questions on the Physiognomy Ascribed to Aristotle,". For some discus­ sion o f Ps.-Aristotelian texts on physiognomy in the Latin medieval world, see Charles Schmitt, "Pseudo-Aristotle in the Latin Middle A ges," in P seu d o -A risto tle in th e M id d le A ges, ed. Jill Kraye, W. F. Ryan, and C. B.</head><label>8643515219091345194196108821893199419819</label><figDesc>For a discussion o f ach eiropoietai, see Ernst Kitzinger, "H ie Cult o f Images in the A ge before Iconoclasm," D u m barton O aks P a p e rs 8 (1954): 112-15See In E vangelium L u cae 8:43, ed. A. Borgnet, O pera omnia, 38 vols. (Paris, 1890-99), 22:580. 7 Boethius briefly discusses physiognomy. See his In terp reta tio p rio ru m an alyticoru m A ris to te lis 2.28 (PL 64:712AS cience a n d the S ecrets o f N atu re: B o o k s o f S ecrets in M e d ie v a l a n d E a rly M o d e m C ulture (Princeton, 1994), 4 5 -4 9Williams, "The Early Circulation o f the Pseudo-Aristotelian S e c re t o f S ecrets in the West: The Papal and Imperial Courts," M icro lo g u s: N atura, scien ze e so c ie tà m edievali, vol. 2: L e scien ze a lia co rte d i F ed erico I I (Tumhout, 1994), 127-44, andesp. 136. 10 Danielle Jacquart suggests that, based on similarities found between Michael Scot's L ib e r p h isio n o m ia e and Ps.-Aristotle's P hysiognom y, perhaps an outline o f the latter was intro­ duced at the court o f Frederick H. See D anielle Jacquart, "La physiognomonie à l 'époque de Frédéric II: Le traité de M ichel Scot," M ic ro lo g u s 2: L e scien ze a lla co rte d i F ed erico II, 25Speculum 18 (1943): 99-103. For a translation o f Ps.- Aristotle's P h ysiogn om on ies, see The C om plete W orks o f A risto tle : The R e v ise d O xford T ranslation, ed. Jonathan Barnes, 2 vols. (Princeton, N.J., 1984), 1:1237-50Schmitt (London, 1986), 6 -7 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1" coords="4,63.34,349.98,340.00,7.20;4,78.24,360.53,331.26,7.20;4,62.89,371.08,346.01,7.20;4,62.89,381.63,346.37,7.20;4,63.09,391.98,188.35,7.20;4,77.99,402.53,330.48,7.20;4,63.07,412.63,126.45,7.20;4,78.22,423.18,330.80,7.20;4,63.82,433.73,345.30,7.20;4,62.87,444.28,345.79,7.20;4,62.62,454.83,346.10,7.20;4,63.57,465.18,346.00,7.20;4,62.87,475.48,345.66,7.20;4,62.87,485.78,346.80,7.25;4,63.82,496.13,263.72,7.20;4,77.96,506.68,330.54,7.20;4,62.87,517.03,345.83,7.20;4,62.86,527.33,97.27,7.20;4,77.96,537.88,331.28,7.20;4,62.61,548.43,345.91,7.20;4,62.61,558.28,346.74,7.20;4,62.86,568.62,345.94,7.20;4,62.86,579.17,346.23,7.20;4,61.86,589.47,346.95,7.20;4,62.61,599.57,345.94,7.20;4,62.36,609.62,170.73,7.20"><head>Court ofFrederick II Hohenstaufen," M ic ro lo g u s 2 : L e scien ze a lia corte d i F ed erico II, 117 . 13 "Phisionomia est doctrina salutis: electio boni et vitatio mali, comprehensio virtutis et praetermissio vitiorum. Hoc autem inducit verus amor d e i. . . " (Michael Scot, L ib e r p h isio n o - m iae, proemium). I have used the Venice edition ( 1477 ). A t least eighteen editions appeared subsequently, indicating the popularity o f the work. 14 Latin text and the book, chapter, and paragraph numbers (or book, treatise, chapter, and paragraph numbers) are from Hermann Stadler's edi­ tion, D e an im alibu s lib ri XXVI, Beiträge zur Geschichte der Philosophie des Mittelalters 15 and 16 (Münster, 1916 - 21 ); the English translation is cited by page number. 16 For a review o f the route by which physiognomy entered into medieval science and phi­ losophy, see Jole Agrimi, "Fisiognomica e '". . . physonomia . . . divinare docet de affectibus hominum per physicas formas mem- brorum" (Albert the Great, D e an im alibu s 1 . 2 . 2 . 126 ; On A nim als, 93 ). No good studies o f A l­ bert's treatment o f physiognomy exist, although two treatments appeared before WWII comparing some o f Albert's views with the racial science o f pre-war Germany. See Hans Scharold's "D ie Physiognomie des Albertus Magnus und die moderne Wissenschaft," B a yerisch e B lä tte r f u r d a s G ym nasial-Schulw esen 68/ 5 ( 1932 ): 289 - 301 ; and F. M. Barbado, "La physionomie, le tempérament et le caractère, d'après Albert le Grand et la science moderne,</head><label>211713147714191621161221269351932289301</label><figDesc>Albert the Great, Q u aestion es su p er d e anim alibus 1.21-22, ed. Ephrem Filthaut, O pera om nia 12 (Munster, 1955), 94-96. 15 See P. G. Meersseman, In trodu ctio in op era om nia B . A lb e rti M a g n i O.P. (Bruges, 1931), 139. N ote too that in D e an im alibu s 23.1.46 Albert alludes to a work o f his own with the title P h yson om ya; see Albertus Magnus, On A n im als: A M e d ie v a l Sum m a Z oologica, frans. Kenneth F. Kitchell, Jr., and Irven Michael Resnick, 2 vols. (Baltimore and London, 1999), 1573. In all references to D e an im alibu s theScolastica,' " M ic ro lo g u s 1 :1 d is c o rsi d e i c o rp i (Tumhout, 1993), 23 5 -7 1 . 17" Revue T hom iste 36 (1931): 314-51.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2" coords="5,44.40,359.76,346.27,8.55;5,44.65,372.71,346.06,8.55;5,44.65,385.91,37.61,8.55;5,55.45,398.41,335.14,8.55;5,44.64,411.11,346.44,8.55;5,44.64,424.31,345.33,8.55;5,44.39,437.26,346.31,8.55;5,59.74,466.63,331.04,7.20;5,44.89,476.93,345.55,7.20;5,44.89,487.48,345.62,7.20;5,45.84,498.28,126.10,7.20;5,59.74,508.38,330.65,7.20;5,44.89,518.68,346.21,7.20;5,44.89,529.23,58.95,7.20;5,59.29,539.58,331.34,7.20;5,45.09,549.63,341.47,7.20;5,59.04,560.23,331.35,7.20;5,44.39,570.53,346.37,7.20;5,44.64,580.83,346.02,7.20;5,44.89,590.68,345.62,7.20;5,44.89,601.02,182.22,7.20;6,62.40,97.66,346.79,8.55;6,63.35,110.41,346.96,8.55;6,63.59,123.11,346.30,8.55;6,63.34,136.56,345.56,8.55;6,63.84,149.26,345.94,8.55;6,63.84,162.01,90.98,8.55;6,74.14,174.96,335.80,8.55;6,63.85,187.41,345.33,8.55;6,63.85,200.41,345.78,8.55;6,63.85,213.36,346.25,8.55;6,63.60,226.31,346.01,8.55;6,64.10,239.26,46.26,8.55"><head>trance through w h ich th e character can b e view ed . . . . F or th is reason a ll th e p h y sio g n o m ists are a s one in claim in g th at th e ey e is th e true m essen ger o f th e h eart." 21 A fter th e ey e s, th e appearance o f th e forehead, n o se, lip s, m outh, hair, ears, n eck , groin and g en ita ls, th e hue o f th e skin, and th e b od y's p osture and m ovem ents seem to p resent th e clearest ind ication s o f character. T he in d ica­ tio n s p rovided b y any one o f th ese alon e w ill b e in su ffic ien t for a secure 18 For a brief discussion o f Constantine's life and sources for his biography, see Marie- Thérèse d'Alvem y, "Translations and Translators," in R en aissan ce a n d R en ew al in the Twelfth Century, ed. Robert L. Benson and Giles Constable, with Carol D. Lariham (Cambridge, M ass., 1982 ; rpt. Toronto, 1991 ), 422 - 26 . 19 For the identity o f Loxus and Palemon, see Albertus Magnus, On A nim als, 94 n. 206 , and Foerster's S crip to res p h ysiogn om on ici G ra eci e t L atin i l:x v iii-x ix ., lxxv-lxxvi, and clxxvii-clxxviii. 20 Albert the Great, Q uaestiones su p e r d e a n im alibu s 1 . 22 , ed. Filthaut, 96 . 6 - 7 : "Maxime enim accipitur physiognomia respecta faciei et partium anteriorum, quae vicinantar cerebro." 21 "In occulis autem principaliter consistit omnis perfectio physonomiae. D ixit enim Palemon occulos esse tamquam flores animae, et animant emicare per occulos, et solam occu- lorum dispositionem esse aditam, per quern animus introspici possit. . . . Propter quod etiam occulum verum cordis esse nuntium affirmaverunt omnes simul physyonomi" (Albert the Great, D e an im alibu s 1 . 2 . 3 . 142 ; On A nim als, 99 ). judgm ent. M ich ael S co t cau tion s that th e p h ysiogn om ist sh ould gath er to ­ geth er th e in d ication s o f th e entire b od y, and con sider a lso a num ber o f other v a ria b les (the p erson 's a g e, p eriod o f resid en ce in a p articu lar area, m edical h isto ry , and other accid en tal con d ition s). 22 B u t w h en th e ind icators are in gen ­ eral agreem ent w ith one another th e p h ysiogn om ist can arrive at a seem in gly sc ie n tific co n clu sion . W h en th e p rin cip les o f th is scien ce are ap plied , th ey can produce a lled g ely relia b le ev a lu ation s o f character. For exam ple, A lb ert th e G reat avers, "R ed­ d ish ey e s th a t b u lg e fo r a lon g tim e sig n ify a lech erou s, vora cio u s p erson . V ery sm a ll, b u lgin g ey es are a strong ind ication o f one w h o is v ery greed y for g a in ." 23 O ne can deduce other character traits from th e appearance o f th e n o se or nostrils:</head><label>21181982199142226199420620122966721123142992223</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3" coords="6,215.79,398.61,193.83,8.55;6,64.30,411.61,345.73,8.55;6,64.10,424.56,345.89,8.55;6,64.10,437.26,119.94,8.55;6,85.45,455.26,324.09,8.55;6,85.45,467.01,324.94,8.55;6,85.45,478.81,324.15,8.55;6,78.24,507.18,152.81,7.20;6,78.49,517.48,331.22,7.20;6,63.59,528.03,345.76,7.20;6,64.30,538.13,123.81,7.20;6,78.24,548.68,330.86,7.20;6,63.59,558.78,345.78,7.20;6,63.59,569.33,345.92,7.20;6,63.84,579.63,345.56,7.20;6,63.09,589.98,346.18,7.20;6,63.34,600.03,346.10,7.20;6,63.59,609.88,81.20,7.20"><head>are so lid and round" ind icate on e w h o is "strong and great-h earted ." In lik e m anner, b o d ily proportions are h eld to be in stru ctive. T h u s, fo llo w in g a d iscu ssio n o f th e anatom y, fu n ction , and shape o f th e g en ita ls, A lb ert adds, Philem on says that the space w hich extends from below the navel [umbilicus] to the bottom o f the pecten [the groin area] must be measured, as must that which extends from the umbilicus to the beginning o f the neck at the clavicles. 22 Michael Scot, L ib e r p h isio n o m ia e 102 . 23 "Stantes [occuli] autem diu et subrubentes libidinosum significant et voracem. Stantes autem et breves valde significant multum avarum lucrorum" (Albert the Great,. 24 "Nares autem cum in extremo acutae sunt, facilem ad iracundiam hominem ostendunt. Crassae autem extra modum nares immundum hominem dant intelligi. Cum ima narium solida sunt rotunda, tamquam sint obtusa, fortem dicunt et magnanimum. Tales enim nares Plato cen- suit dari leoninis hominibus et caninis generosis, eo quod in leonibus et caxiibus generosis tales nares videbat. Dicebat enim, quod quaecumque similitudo animalium aliquorum in hominibus est, quod et homines talium imitantur mores anim alium. . ." (ibid. 1 . 2 . 8 .</head><label>221022324128</label><figDesc>D e a n im alibu s 1..2.3.144; O n A nim als, 100-101)223; On A nim als, 129- 30, slightly modified).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4" coords="7,64.80,87.81,324.54,8.55;7,65.05,99.36,323.70,8.55;7,65.30,111.11,325.14,8.55;7,65.30,123.11,324.32,8.55;7,65.05,135.11,324.00,8.55;7,65.50,147.11,323.54,8.55;7,65.30,158.86,324.38,8.55;7,65.05,170.61,324.00,8.55;7,65.50,182.61,284.70,8.55;7,54.50,201.61,335.41,8.55;7,43.90,214.56,263.74,8.55;7,65.50,232.31,323.83,8.55;7,65.75,244.31,323.97,8.55;7,65.50,256.06,324.40,8.55;7,65.75,268.06,323.79,8.55;7,65.75,280.06,125.95,8.55"><head>For these distances are naturally equal in a fully extended man. I f it is equal, then th is signifies praiseworthy mental power and bodily disposition. If, how­ ever, the chest is longer, the power o f the mind w ill overcome the condition o f the b o d y .. . . But i f the span o f the belly is longer than that above, the man w ill be voluptuous and a fornicator.. . . Loxus says that a softer, fairly con­ cave belly is a sign o f power and m agnificence o f the mind. A ristotle, how­ ever, says that one who has a large belly is indiscrete, dull, haughty, and loves the act o f intercourse. A moderate sized belly, along w ith a corresponding nar­ rowing o f the chest, indicates loftiness o f intellect and good counsel. 25 Finally, n ot only do the members o f the body reveal the accidental attributes o f the sou l (i.e ., character), but so too do the body's movements: A person's gait, proceeding as it does from the inclination o f his nature, an­ nounces what his mind is like and what h is habits are. Thus, those who go forward w ith long steps are shown to be great-hearted and effective, w hile those who go forward with shortened steps are ineffective, pusillanim ous, n ig­ gardly, and afflicted by grief. 26</head><label>2526</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5" coords="7,43.89,350.41,345.64,8.55;7,44.14,363.36,345.67,8.55;7,44.14,376.56,345.33,8.55;7,44.39,389.51,345.18,8.55;7,44.39,402.46,345.23,8.55;7,43.69,415.41,346.26,8.55;7,58.79,456.53,331.60,7.20;7,44.39,466.63,345.75,7.20;7,44.39,476.93,345.85,7.20;7,44.14,487.48,345.98,7.20;7,44.64,497.83,344.94,7.20;7,44.39,508.13,345.93,7.20;7,44.14,518.68,346.00,7.20;7,44.39,529.03,345.74,7.20;7,44.64,539.33,344.57,7.20;7,44.14,549.63,345.74,7.20;7,44.13,559.98,313.56,7.20;7,58.78,570.28,331.40,7.20;7,44.38,580.83,345.87,7.20;7,44.38,590.93,345.71,7.20;7,44.13,601.03,305.76,7.20"><head>w ith a sch o la stic in clin ation to enum erate and catalogu e evid en ce draw n from p h ysiogn om y. T his p atien ce w ill b e rewarded, sin ce th is evid en ce w a s u tilized in th e M id dle A g es n ot o n ly as a g u id e to th e character and h ab its o f in d ivid u ­ a ls, b ut a lso a s an eth n ological indicator o f th e character o f p eo p les or races. T he Polem onis de physiognom onia liber d evotes a go o d d eal o f atten tion to th e ch aracteristics o f th e inhabitants o f variou s regions, id en tifyin g th e G reeks 25 "D icit enim Phylemon metiendum esse spatium, quod est ab umbilico inferius usque ad iirnun pectinis, et spatium quod est ab umbilico usque ad colli iuitium in furculis: hoc enim in bene extenso homine secundum naturam aequale est: et siquidem aequale est, laudabilem sig- nificat et animi virtutem et corporis dispositionem. Si autem pectus longius sit, vincet animi virtus corporis habitudinem. . . . Si autem spatium ventris vincit spatium superius, erit fornica­ tor et voluptuosus.. . . Ventrem autem molliorem atque impressiorem virtutem animi et mag- nificentiam dicit Loxus significare. Aristoteles autem dicit, quod qui magnum ventrem habet, est indiscretus, stolidus, superbus et coitum amans. Mediocritas autem ventris cum competenti strictura pectoris significat altitudinem intellectus et boni consilii" (ibid. 1 . 2 . 24 . 469 ; On A n i­ m als, 225 , modified). For a discussion o f some o f these indicators, see Sebastian Killermann, 'D ie somatische Anthropologie bei Albertus Magnus," A ngelicum 21 ( 1944 ): 224 - 69 . 26 "Incessus quoque hominis ex inclinatione naturae procedens annuntiat de eo qualis sit animi et qualium morum: qui enim longis passibus incedunt, magnanimi esse significantur et efficaces. Qui vero angustis passibus incedunt, inefficaces sunt parvae mentis et parci atque dolore astricti. . ." (Albert the Great, D e an im alibu s 1 . 2 . 26 . 510 ;</head><label>251224469225194422469261226510</label><figDesc>On A nim als, 241).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6" coords="8,61.71,423.88,97.61,7.20;8,77.51,434.43,331.51,7.20;8,62.90,445.03,345.94,7.20;8,62.90,455.58,345.87,7.20;8,62.90,465.88,346.19,7.20;8,62.40,475.98,346.34,7.20;8,62.40,486.53,346.60,7.20;8,62.40,497.08,189.15,7.20;8,77.30,507.63,331.50,7.20;8,62.65,517.98,346.26,7.20;8,62.90,528.28,345.83,7.20;8,62.90,538.83,345.18,7.20;8,62.89,549.18,345.34,7.20;8,62.39,559.48,345.89,7.20;8,62.39,569.83,346.37,7.20;8,62.64,580.38,345.90,7.20;8,62.14,590.43,346.82,7.20;8,62.14,600.28,346.01,7.20;8,63.09,610.38,101.22,7.20;9,63.60,88.31,324.21,8.55;9,64.10,100.31,324.45,8.55;9,64.30,112.06,323.98,8.55;9,64.30,123.61,324.19,8.55;9,64.30,135.61,324.30,8.55;9,64.10,147.61,324.55,8.55;9,64.10,159.36,324.93,8.55;9,63.85,171.11,324.79,8.55;9,64.55,183.11,324.33,8.55;9,64.30,195.11,184.29,8.55;9,54.00,213.38,334.84,9.45;9,42.95,227.26,44.98,8.55"><head>p h ysiogn om on ici, 2 "In calida regione sunt gentes native brunae in pelle: ut patet de aethyopibus. . . . Et in crine [reading crin e for cane] sunt siccae: crispae: capillos habent et grossos et asperos. Et in frigida regione nascuntur gentes longae: in pelle multum albae aut blundae: nudae a p ilis vel quasi qui in suo esse sunt extensi albi vel blundi. Nota quia regio est multiplex in provincia et matrice mulieris: quae si utraque fuerit calida creatura generatur: et generata manet nigra vel bruna et caetera. Et si fuerit frigida efficitur alba plus et minus secundum regionis com- plexionem" (Michael Scot, L ib e rp h isio n o m ia e 43 ). 29 "Diversantur etiam pili secundum diversitatem regionum, ideo quod diversitas habita- tionis diversitatem facit complexionum etiam in habitantibus in eis: quoniam pili hominum qui sunt in locis calidis, sunt duri et crispi sicut sunt pili Ethiopum: et habitantibus in locis frigidis suntm olles . . ." (Albert the Great,), where Albert explains that curly hair results from the dryness and earthi­ ness in the vapor in the hair's matter, and "Ethiopians . . . who dwell in hot and dry places, have curly hair, rather like grains o f pepper. They have this due both to the dryness o f the vapor and to the dryness o f the exterior, surrounding air" ("Ethyopes autem in siccis et calidis locis habitantes pilos crispos ad modum granorum piperis habent turn propter siccitatem vaporis turn propter siccitatem exterioris aerem continentis"). Cf. Albert's Q u aestion es su p e r d e an im alibu s 19 . 7 - 9 , ed. Filthaut, 305 - 7 . Erect hair, either black or the color o f water, and which is dirty and coarse, be­ speaks a violent character. Such people are like the boar or p ig which has this sort o f hair and the boar is violent, as is the pig. Soft hair, however, that is sparse and ultra-fine, indicates a lack o f red blood and bespeaks a dull, slow character. I f the hair is too curly, it is giving notice o f a crafty, harsh, tim id person who is greedy. I f the hair is pressed down too much and hangs over the forehead, it announces a w ild character and in this it resembles the hair on a bear's head, w hich is the reason Plato called such men "ursine." . . . Blond hair and thick white hair say the people are ignorant and fierce. Such is the hair o f those who live very far to the North. 30 S im ila rly , ju s t a s hair color can sa y a great d eal ab ou t a p eo p le so to o for skin color:</head><label>243291979305730</label><figDesc>D e an im alibu s 3.2.2.82; On A nim als, 385). See also 19.6.28 {On A nim als, 1346</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7" coords="9,43.18,350.16,346.61,8.55;9,57.58,393.88,331.78,7.20;9,43.18,404.68,346.02,7.20;9,43.18,415.03,345.22,7.20;9,43.18,425.38,346.02,7.20;9,42.93,435.88,345.98,7.20;9,43.18,446.43,345.90,7.20;9,43.18,456.78,345.78,7.20;9,43.18,466.83,345.58,7.20;9,43.18,477.43,203.27,7.20;9,57.59,487.73,331.66,7.20;9,42.94,498.28,345.46,7.20;9,42.69,508.83,346.53,7.20;9,42.69,519.43,346.37,7.20;9,42.69,529.73,37.80,7.20"><head>organs and operations; and to eth n ology or an thropology fo r a d isc u ssio n o f 30 ". . . capilli stabiles vel nigri vel aquatici colons sordidi et crassi animum indicant violentum: et apro sunt sim iles tales vel sui quae talem habet capillaturam, et violentus est aper et etiam sus. Capilli autem molles et ran et ultra modum tenues rubei penuriam indicant san­ guinis, et ebes ingenium et pigrum praeloquuntur. Si autem sint capilli minium crispi, pronun- tiant subdolum, asperum, timidum et lucri cupidum. Capilli vero depressi nimium et fronti imminentes ferum declarant animum: et hiis concordat capitis ursini capillatura: propter quod et tales ursinos homines Plato esse pronuntiavit. . . . Capilli autem flavi et crassi albidi, indociles dicunt esse et feros, sicut est capillatura eorum qui multum sunt ad Aquilonem" (Albert the Great, 31 "Physonomia autem huius assignatur a Phylemone sapiente, qui dicit, quod color niger lenis versutum indicat et imbecillem et refertur ad habitatores qui habitant quatuor prima cli­ mata. Color autem albus rubeus, fortes et animosos ostendit: et hie est habitantium in Germania praecipue et habitatorum sexti et septimi climatum" (ibid. 1 .</head><label>30311</label><figDesc>D e a n im alibu s 1.2.2.132-33; On A nim als, 9 5 -6)3.7.623; On A nim als, 284, slightly modified).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8" coords="10,62.16,349.41,346.71,8.55;10,61.91,362.41,347.32,8.55;10,60.71,375.61,346.54,8.55;10,61.21,388.56,303.04,8.55;10,359.51,388.56,48.52,8.55;10,61.90,401.51,345.39,8.55;10,61.90,414.46,345.11,8.55;10,61.45,427.20,346.60,8.55;10,61.89,440.15,345.67,8.55;10,61.89,453.10,346.16,8.55;10,61.89,465.80,345.89,8.55;10,61.70,478.80,345.58,8.55;10,61.70,491.80,345.95,8.55;10,61.70,504.45,150.23,8.55;10,75.85,539.08,331.60,7.20;10,62.14,549.18,66.58,7.20;10,75.59,559.72,330.93,7.20;10,60.94,570.02,346.40,7.20;10,61.20,580.37,346.00,7.20;10,61.70,590.42,337.78,7.20;10,75.60,600.52,331.41,7.20;10,60.95,610.62,305.46,7.20"><head>shared b etw een m edicin e and physiognom y: in particular, th e doctrine o f com p lexion . A ccord in g to A vicen n a's d efin ition in h is in flu en tial Canon o f M edicine, "co m p lexion is that q u ality w h ich resu lts from th e m utual interac­ tio n . . . o f th e fou r prim ary q u alities resid in g w ith in th e elem en ts." 3 2 33 T he fou r elem en ts-air, fire, earth, and w ater-com bine in m aterial b od ies and are a s­ so cia ted w ith th e fou r prim ary q u alities-th e hot, cold , m oist, and dry. C om ­ p le x io n , th en , resu lts from th e interaction o f th ese q u alities, to produce co m p o site b o d ies th at are h ot and dry (ch oleric), h ot and m o ist (san gu in eou s), co ld and m o ist (p h legm atic), cold and dry (m elan ch olic), or, w hen th e fou r q u alities are equal, tem perate or b alanced. A lth ou gh som e w ou ld relegate the doctrine o f co m p lexion -so central to p hysiogn om y-to th e stu dy o f m ed i­ cin e, 34 n everth eless an understanding o f its p rin cip les had a bearing on both sp ecu la tiv e and p ractical th eo lo g y . 32 See especially Walter Clyde Curry,. Edward Grant (Cambridge, M ass., 1974 ), 717 . This selection reprints portions from A T reatise on the C anon o f M ed icin e o f A vicenna, frans. O. Cameron Grüner (London, 1930 ), although the translation has been modified for Grant's volume by M ichael McVaugh. 34 Helinand o f Froidment, D e cogn ition e su i 8 (PL 212:729B): "Corporis humani cognitio in duobus est, in materia scilicet et forma. Complexionem autem medicis relinquo"</head><label>333343219747171930348</label><figDesc>C h au cer a n d the M e d ie v a l S ciences (N ew York, 1960), chaps. 3-4. 33 Avicenna, C anon 1 .1 .3 .1 .1 have used the translation found in A S ou rce B o o k in M e d ie ­ v a l Science, ed</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9" coords="11,70.35,165.81,320.69,8.55;11,45.11,178.56,345.55,8.55;11,44.41,191.51,328.02,8.55;11,56.16,204.71,334.10,8.55;11,44.66,217.66,345.69,8.55;11,44.91,230.61,346.30,8.55;11,44.91,243.36,346.96,8.55;11,45.37,256.31,107.96,8.55"><head>, R ob ert G rosseteste recom m ends that clerics sh ould im p ose p en ance o n ly after h avin g g iv en due con sideration to com p lexion , sin ce com p lexion h as a b earing on an in d ivid u al's a b ility to w ithstand th e in clin ation to sin . 36 S p ecu la tiv e th eo lo g y turned to p hysiogn om y and th e doctrine o f com ­ p le x io n in an altogether d ifferen t w ay. R ather than argu ing from ou ter to inner, from th e appearance o f th e b od y to th e con d ition o f th e so u l, one m ay argue from th e s o u l's con d ition to th e appearance o f th e body. W illiam o f C on ch es, fo r exam ple, g</head><label>36</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10" coords="11,44.92,333.81,346.87,8.55;11,45.12,346.81,345.99,8.55;11,45.37,360.01,345.94,8.55;11,45.62,372.71,345.64,8.55;11,45.12,385.41,345.04,8.55;11,44.92,398.41,346.29,8.55;11,45.37,411.11,93.54,8.55;11,59.77,435.63,331.78,7.20;11,44.92,446.23,346.38,7.20;11,45.12,456.53,346.51,7.20;11,45.12,466.83,346.31,7.20;11,44.92,477.18,345.94,7.20;11,45.37,487.73,252.19,7.20;11,59.52,498.03,331.46,7.20;11,45.12,508.38,346.12,7.20;11,44.92,518.68,302.57,7.20;11,59.52,529.03,331.69,7.20;11,44.92,539.33,346.18,7.20;11,44.92,549.43,345.62,7.20;11,45.12,559.73,345.74,7.20;11,45.87,570.03,344.10,7.20;11,44.92,580.62,346.13,7.20;11,45.12,590.42,184.18,7.20;11,59.07,600.77,298.69,7.20"><head>to fad e aw ay. . . . H is d escendants, th erefore, b o m as th ey w ere from a corrupt an cestor, h a v e a ll b een corrupted, and n ever afterw ard has p erfect h ealth been fou n d in hum ans." 37 S im ilarly, had E ve n o t sinned and rem ained in Paradise sh e w o u ld h ave rem ained h ale, H ildegard o f B ingen affirm s, and avoid ed th e w om an 's "cu rse" or punishm ent-th e m onthly flu x o f b lood , m enstruation- w h ich n o w is n ecessa ry to purge a w om an 's b od y o f im purities stem m ing from its corruption. 38 35 "Complexio etiam peccatoris consideranda est, secundum quod ex signis exterioribus perpendi potest; quia secundum diversas complexiones, unus magis impellitur ad unum pecca- tum, quam alius. Quia si cholericus magis impellitur ad iram, sed melancholicus magis ad odium" (Alain de Lille, L ib e r p o e n ite n tia lis 1. 17 , ed. Jean Longere, Analecta mediaevalia Na- murcensia 18, 2 vols. [Louvain, 1965 ], 2 : 31 ). N ote that the edition in PL 210:287D adds, fol­ lowing this passage, "si sanguineus, vel phlegmaticus, ad luxuriam." 36 Robert Grosseteste, Templum D e i 19 . 9 , ed. Joseph Goering and F. A. C. Mantello, Toronto M edieval Latin Texts (Toronto, 1984 ), 64 : "Hec sunt diligenter consideranda in peni- tencia iniungenda. . . . Complexio: si colericus, uel sanguineus, uel melancolicus." 37 "Primus enim homo inter quatuor qualitates fuit temperatus. Sed postquam amoenitate paradisi exp u lsu s. . . cepit desiccari atque naturalis calor extingui. . . . Omnes igitur ex eo nati, utpote ex coirupto, sunt corrupti, neque postea perfecta sanitas in homine fuit inuenta" (W il­ liam o f Conches, D ragm aticon P h ilosoph iae 6.1 3 . 2 - 3 , ed. Italo Ronca, CCCM 152 [Tumhout, 1997 ], 227 ). A translation appeared as A D ia lo g u e on N a tu ra l P h ilo so p h y (D ragm aticon P h i­ losophiae), trans. Italo Ronca and Matthew Curr (Notre Dame, 1997), 147 . See also Honorius o f Autun, D e p h ilo s o p h ia m undi 23 (PL 172:55D). 38 Hildegard o f Bingen, C au sae e t C urae 3, ed. Paul Kaiser (Leipzig, 1903), 103 .</head><label>37381719652313619919846437231997227147103</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11" coords="12,357.76,134.86,47.60,8.55;12,59.50,146.93,345.62,9.45;12,59.49,159.63,346.76,9.45;12,59.28,173.51,345.75,8.55;12,59.73,186.21,345.96,8.55;12,59.73,199.21,345.71,8.55;12,59.48,211.73,346.30,9.45;12,59.48,225.36,345.87,8.55;12,59.48,238.06,313.69,8.55"><head>ore c lo se ly resem b les a h eaven ly b od y owing to a balan ced com p lexion p articip atin g le ss in contrary q u alities-from w h ich ce lestia l b od ies are altogether free. . . .,,4° Y e t sin c e A dam 's fa ll is resp on sib le for b o d ily corruption am ong h is d escen ­ dants, it fo llo w s to o th at an id eal hum an com p lexion w ill be rediscovered on ly in th o se unburdened b y origin al sin: n am ely, M ary and Jesu s, for th ey alon e, in th is life , w ere "ab so lu tely p erfect." 41 T he lo g ic o f th is p o sitio n rooted in p h ysiogn om y m u st h ave been reasonab ly com pellin g. T hom as A q uin as w as acq uainted w ith th e argum ent th at Jesus had to h ave d isp layed th e b</head><label>41</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12" coords="12,74.13,349.23,331.25,7.20;12,59.48,359.83,257.34,7.20;12,73.87,370.13,331.70,7.20;12,59.47,380.43,346.53,7.20;12,59.72,390.78,345.34,7.20;12,59.46,401.33,336.34,7.20;12,74.10,411.88,331.80,7.20;12,59.70,422.43,297.31,7.20"><head>39 See Albert the Great, Q uaestion es su p er d e an im alibu s 6 . 24 - 26 , ed. Filthaut, 168 . 25 , where Albert attributes this view to Avicenna (see the C anon 1. 1 . 6 . 3 ). 40 ". . . homo inter omnia plus accedit ad similitudinem corporis caelestis, propter aequali- tatem complexionis minus participans qualitates contrarias, a quibus corpora caelestia sunt omnino libera . . ." {S u per D ion ysiu m d e ecclesia stica h ierarch ia 5, ed. Maria Burger, O pera om nia 36/ 2 [Munster, 1999 ], 123 . 2 - 7 ; see also D e a n im alibu s 12 . 1 . 4 . 55 ; On A nim als, 914 ). 41 So, notes Albert, "nullus in hac vita perfectus fuit simpliciter nisi lesus Christus et mater eius . . ."</head><label>624261682516340219991232712145591441</label><figDesc>{S u p erD io n ysiu m d e e c clesia stica h ierarch ia 1, ed. Burger, 13.10-11).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13" coords="12,378.43,474.87,26.55,6.75;12,59.23,485.08,345.98,7.20;12,59.23,495.63,345.66,7.20;12,59.23,505.98,345.62,7.20;12,58.73,516.28,346.11,7.20;12,59.23,526.63,345.84,7.20;12,59.23,537.18,346.21,7.20;12,58.73,547.73,346.20,7.20;12,59.67,557.82,327.75,7.20;12,73.37,568.12,331.94,7.20;12,58.71,578.22,346.69,7.20;12,58.96,588.52,345.70,7.20;12,59.41,598.37,29.10,7.20;12,73.36,608.42,331.74,7.20;13,52.10,88.81,334.06,8.55;13,40.55,101.26,345.56,8.55;13,40.80,114.01,346.13,8.55;13,39.85,127.21,347.12,8.55;13,41.05,140.16,345.79,8.55;13,41.05,153.36,345.96,8.55;13,41.05,165.38,345.67,9.45;13,40.79,178.81,203.35,8.55"><head>Sum m a th eo lo g ia e 3 . 46 .6c.: "with respect to the body he had the best complexion because his body was fashioned miraculously by the operation o f the Holy Spirit" ("nam et secundum corpus erat op­ time complexionatus, cum corpus ejus fuerit formatum miraculose operatione Spiritus Sancti"). Albert the Great also indicates that because o f Adam's sin, his semen was corrupted and there­ fore among those who descend materially from his seed the operative or formative power o f the semen fails to fashion a human in the condition Adam had known previously. See his S u per argum entum H ieronym i, in S u per M atthaeum , ed. B. Schmidt, O pera om nia 21/ 1 (Mllnster, 1987 ), 8 . 43 - 47 . Jesus' miraculous birth places him outside this material chain o f descent. 43 "Et quia secundum merita materiae dantur formae, sicut Plato dixit, et unicuique com- plexioni propria respondet forma, ideo aequaliori complexioni debetur anima nobilissima ..." (Albert the Great, D e an im a 2 . 3 . 23 , ed. Clemens Stroick, O pera om nia 7/ 1 [Munster, 1968 ], 133 . 22 ). 44 "E x parte enim camis erat teneritudo naturae optime complexionatae; et quanto natura S till, n one o f th e exam ples cited ab ove p rovide anything lik e an in v estig a ­ tio n into th e p h ysiogn om y o f M ary or Jesu s. There is , h ow ever, su ch an in ­ v estig a tio n in a w ork im properly attributed to A lb ert th e G reat, entitled the M ariale or th e C C X X X quaestiones super Evangelium "M issus est. " 45 T he authorship o f th is te x t rem ains m uch in doubt. M eerssem an and in itia lly P elster w ere in clin ed to treat it as authentic-indeed, perhaps a s A lb ert's ea rliest w riting. 46 M ore recent stu d ies b y F ries, K orosak, P elster and K olpin g, h ow ever, h ave rejected A lb ert's authorship.</head><label>34611987843474323231196813322444546</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14" coords="13,41.27,508.38,345.94,7.20;13,41.47,518.93,153.48,7.20;13,55.67,529.23,331.43,7.20;13,41.01,539.58,346.46,7.20;13,40.51,549.63,166.96,7.20;13,55.66,559.97,329.60,7.20;13,55.66,570.02,331.02,7.20;13,41.00,580.37,346.17,7.20;13,40.75,590.22,345.99,7.20;13,41.45,600.52,85.48,7.20"><head>yet identified a probable author, and these scholars also disagree on the likely date for the work, situating it between about 1240 and 1300. 48 Johannes Beumer, "D ie literarischen Beziehungen zwischen dem Senno VI D e Assum- tione B M V (Pseudo-Bonaventura) und dem Mariale oder Laus Virginis (Pseudo-Albertus)," F ranziskanischen Studien 44 ( 1962 ): 455 - 60 . 49 See Kolping, "Zur Frage des Textgeschichte, Herkunft und Entstehungszeit," 2 88 - 305 . 50 Despite the opinion o f Augustine, that w e simply do not know what Mary looked like: "Neque enim nouimus faciem uirginis Mariae, ex qua ille a uiro intacta neque in ipso partu cor- rapta mirabiliter natus est" (D e trin ita te 8. 5 . 7 , ed. W. J. Mountain and Fr. Glorie, CCL 50 [Tumhout, 1968 ], 277 ).</head><label>481962455604928830550571968277</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15" coords="14,60.25,265.41,346.77,8.55;14,60.25,278.16,334.49,8.55;14,75.10,319.23,331.47,7.20;14,60.50,329.83,346.37,7.20;14,60.25,340.38,346.70,7.20;14,60.50,350.43,345.45,7.20;14,60.50,361.03,345.97,7.20;14,60.50,371.33,158.31,7.20;14,75.10,381.88,331.26,7.20;14,60.70,392.43,345.70,7.20;14,60.25,402.78,345.36,7.20;14,60.50,413.33,345.78,7.20;14,60.25,423.88,346.70,7.20;14,60.25,433.98,346.27,7.20;14,60.25,444.53,345.53,7.20;14,60.00,455.08,346.21,7.20;14,60.95,465.63,331.01,7.20;14,75.09,475.98,331.52,7.20;14,60.24,486.53,346.46,7.20;14,60.24,496.83,345.99,7.20;14,60.24,507.43,345.90,7.20;14,59.49,517.48,115.20,7.20;14,74.89,528.03,331.56,7.20;14,60.24,538.62,346.02,7.20;14,60.24,548.42,61.21,7.20;14,74.64,559.22,330.54,7.20;14,60.24,569.32,346.44,7.20;14,60.24,579.42,131.76,7.20;14,74.64,589.97,331.62,7.20;14,59.99,599.82,235.72,7.20"><head>re flec t her nature-w h ich ou ght to b e w arm , 55 sin ce it is a w arm nature th at w ill b est h ig h ligh t, b y contrast, her ch astity56 and th e fu lln e ss o f g ra ce in her. 51 Galen remarks, "Si eucraton cerebrum existit secundum quattuor qualitates . . . talibus infantibus quidem existentibus hunt capilli subruffi; pueris vero subrubei: perfectis vero sunt rubei medii quodammmodo existentes crisporum et simplicium, neque calvi fiunt facilius" (M ic ro te g n i II, fol. 12ra, in O pera G aleni, ed. Diomedes Bonardus [Venice: P. Pincius, 1490 ]). The Latin translation is by Constantine the African. M y thanks to Luke Demaitre for locating this and other passages attributed to Galen. 52 "Ergo ad eucraticum corpus pertinet nigredo in capillis secundum Constantinum. Et sic etiam videtur controversia inter Constantinum et Galenum: cum hie nigrum capillorum colorem ponat in aequali corpore, ille autemrubeum" (Ps.Constantine does suggest that the human body having the best complexion (warm and moist) w ill produce straight, black hair and a ruddy or pinkish skin color: "S i corpus est humidum erit pingue et cam eu m .. . . Si calidum et humidum fuerit, nim ie est camis parve pinguedinis. Pili nigri atque plani. tactus calidus et humidus. color albi et rufi medius"). For the importance and influence o f the Pantegni, se e n . 62 below. 53 "... sed dicit Philosophus, quod extrema sunt magis sensitiva et motiva: ergo albedo et nigredo quae sunt extremi colores, magis perfecti sunt in ratione colorum: ergo alter eorum erit in corpore perfectissimo . . . in perfecto corpore potius erit effectus lucis quam tenebrarum: hie autem est albedo: ergo corpus perfectissimum potius erit album quam nigrum" (Ps.-Albert, M a ria le 18. 3 , ed. Borgnet, 41 ). 54 "Videtur potius, quod debuit fuisse rubeum: corpus enim eucraticum est maxime san- guineae complexionis: ergo corpus optime complexionatum debuit esse rubeum" (ibid. 18 . 5 [a], ed. Borgnet, 41 ). 55 "Quaeritur de colore cutis et venustate.. . . Et videtur, quod debuit esse nigra in cute. . .. Quod non albedo, patet: quia albedo est color corporis in quo est abundantia frigiditatis ..." (ibid. 18 and 18. 2 , ed. Borgnet, 41 ). 56 "Item Philosophus [dicit] . . . medium virtutis est pati nec deduci: ergo virtuosior est castitas, ubi major passio a contrario: hoc autem est in calidis</head><label>555114905262533415418541551824156</label><figDesc>-Albert, M a ria le 19.2.2, ed. Borgnet, 43^14).(L ' A rte u n iversale d ella m edicin a (Pantegni). P a rte 1 -L ib ro 1, trans. Marco T. Malato and Umberto de Martini [Rome, 1 9 6 1 ],chap. 1 7 ,p. 65</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16" coords="15,369.58,114.96,18.31,8.55;15,42.25,127.23,346.33,9.45;15,42.50,140.86,213.76,8.55;15,53.05,153.61,335.75,8.55;15,42.70,166.31,345.17,8.55;15,42.70,179.01,345.87,8.55;15,42.49,192.01,347.45,8.55;15,42.49,205.21,345.59,8.55;15,42.70,218.16,345.89,8.55;15,42.49,230.86,345.48,8.55;15,42.49,243.81,346.51,8.55;15,42.69,256.81,330.34,8.55"><head>e tc .) w h ile b la ck e y e s, a s Johannitius sa y s, fo llo w from a d efect in th e v isib le sp irit or a p a u city o f th e crystallin e hum or in th e e y e . 57 U ltim a tely , h ow ever, fo r P s.-A lb ert it is th e brain's com p lexion th at m u st determ ine th e V irg in 's ey e and hair color, sin ce "w e sa y th at th e h air co lo r in ­ d ica tes th e im m ediate d isp osition o f th e brain [cerebrum]. F or th is reason , th e b est h air co lo r sh ould b e determ ined b y th e b e st com p lexion o f th e b rain ." 58 T he b rain 's "b est" com p lexion , h ow ever, can b e determ ined in tw o w ays: eith er a s it is ordered to th e natural p ow er or fa cu lty [yirtus], th at is to the p ow er in trin sic to th e principal m em bers-heart, liv er, and stom ach, etc.-to perform th eir sp e c ific operations; or, as it is ordered to th e anim al virtu e or fa cu lty . In th e fir st in stan ce, w hen ordered to th e natural fa c u lty , th e b</head><label>5758</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17" coords="15,57.09,362.93,331.76,7.20;15,42.94,373.48,345.09,7.20;15,42.69,383.83,345.55,7.20;15,42.48,394.13,345.65,7.20;15,42.94,404.68,344.69,7.20;15,43.20,415.37,19.66,6.75"><head>57 Ibid. 20 . 1 , ed. Borgnet, 4 4 - 4 5 . Johannitius is the Latin name given to Hunayn ibn Ishaq al-'Ibadl ( 8097 - 873 ), a Nestorian Christian physician to the caliph al-Mutawakkil and trans­ lator o f numerous Greek medical works into Arabic. A n abridged version o f his Q uaestion es m edicinae w as translated by Constantine the African and circulated under the</head><label>2014458097873</label><figDesc>title Isagoge, be­ coming a part o f the A rticella , or medical curriculum, in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries. The B</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18" coords="15,42.67,456.78,346.32,7.20;15,42.67,467.08,307.62,7.20;15,57.07,477.43,331.49,7.20;15,42.92,487.98,345.44,7.20;15,41.72,498.53,115.01,7.20;15,56.87,508.63,331.83,7.20;15,42.67,519.18,345.74,7.20;15,42.67,529.48,346.10,7.20;15,42.22,540.03,346.60,7.20;15,42.67,550.12,94.70,7.20"><head>Danielle Jacquart (Leiden, 1994 ), 16 - 43 . For an English translation, drawn from John Gad- desderis R o sa M edicin ae, se e S ou rce B o o k in M e d ie v a l Science, ed. Grant, 705 - 15 . 58 "Dicimus quod color in capillis immediatam signat dispositionem cerebri. Unde optimus color in capillis, debet determinari secundum optimam cerebri complexionem" (Ps.-Albert, M a ria le 20. 3 , ed. Borgnet, 46 ). 59 "Optima autem cerebri complexio determinatur secundum duos modos. Uno modo est cerebrum optime complexionatum, quando est optime ordinatum ad actionem naturalis virtutis, ita quod operationes cerebri maxime ordinantur secundum qualitates ad operationes cordis, et hepatis, et stomachi, et aliorum membrorum principalium. Et secundum hoc cerebrum debet esse calidum et humidum.</head><label>19941643705155834659</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19" coords="16,353.54,227.51,52.76,8.55;16,60.50,240.21,213.55,8.55;16,82.10,257.33,324.53,9.45;16,81.85,270.01,325.03,8.55;16,82.30,281.76,324.60,8.55;16,82.10,293.08,325.11,9.45;16,82.10,305.33,323.99,9.45;16,81.85,317.08,76.41,9.45;17,42.25,88.58,345.40,9.45;17,41.30,102.01,345.64,8.55;17,41.50,114.71,346.48,8.55;17,42.00,127.66,49.56,8.55"><head>rified in th e arteries th a t form a m esh at th e b a se o f th e brain. This newly-formed animal spirit then proceeds up two further arteries into the forepart o f the brain where it is purified once again and the waste products are ejected through the palate and the nostrils. From here the spirit may pass to the middle and back part o f the b ra in .. . . In the back part o f the brain the spirit causes memory, in the front part sense and "fantasia," in the middle part in ­ tellectand flo w through th e arteries to th e brain and th ere, ow in g to th e cold ­ n ess o f th e brain . . . th ese becom e anim al sp irits. A nd th en th ese [anim al sp irits] are</head><label></label><figDesc>or reason.62 Sim ilarly, A lbert the G reat affirm s th a t "the vital spirits are generated in the heart</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20" coords="17,232.91,153.61,7.31,8.55;17,52.55,166.31,335.51,8.55;17,42.25,179.26,346.36,8.55;17,42.00,192.01,345.76,8.55;17,41.50,205.21,346.72,8.55;17,42.00,218.16,211.87,8.55;17,64.10,235.91,325.01,8.55;17,63.60,247.91,324.23,8.55;17,63.85,259.66,325.26,8.55;17,63.85,271.66,323.76,8.55;17,63.85,283.66,323.72,8.55;17,63.60,295.66,324.69,8.55;17,64.10,307.41,324.21,8.55;17,64.10,319.41,259.70,8.55;17,42.50,337.91,345.47,8.55;17,42.50,351.11,113.67,8.55;17,64.10,369.11,323.71,8.55;17,63.85,380.86,324.51,8.55;17,56.90,415.23,331.18,7.20;17,42.00,425.83,346.33,7.20;17,42.00,436.13,113.18,7.20"><head>64 F or th e author o f th e M ariale, lik e W illiam o f C onches and M ich ael S co t (fo r w hom a w arm and dry com p lexion in th e brain in d icates a p erson o f quick w it and in tellig en ce), 65 th e b rain 's com p lexion th at b e st a cc o mm odates th e anim al fa c u lty and therefore is b est su ited to th e p ro cess o f cogn ition and apprehension w ill b e w arm and dry. H e d eclares, Since the well-balanced brain is best ordered in one respect to the actions o f the anim al virtue and in another respect to the operation o f the natural virtue, and the operation o f the animal virtue w ill be more noble than the operation o f the natural virtue, that brain w hich is properly w ell-balanced toward the ani­ mal operations w ill be more noble than that oriented toward the natural opera­ tions. Therefore a brain o f the most perfect and noble body ought to be warm and dry. Since then the body o f our Lady w ill have been the most perfect w ith respect to all her members, she had a warm and dry b r a in .. . , 66 T he co m p lex io n o f M ary's brain m ay d istin gu ish her from m o st other w om en, sin ce fo r A lb ert th e G reat, a woman is less suited to good customs than is a male. For a fem ale's com­ plexion is more m oist than a m ale's, but it belongs to a m oist com plexion to 63 "Spiritus enim vitales generantur in corde et fluunt per arterias usque ad cerebrum et ibi per frigiditatem cerebri. . . hunt illi spiritus animales. Et deinde mittuntur usque ad sensus par- ticulares . . ." (Albert the Great</head><label>64656663</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21" coords="17,56.89,498.53,330.01,7.20;17,42.50,508.83,345.75,7.20;17,42.25,519.43,228.25,7.20;17,56.89,529.73,148.00,7.20;17,56.90,540.28,331.24,7.20;17,42.25,550.38,345.99,7.20;17,42.25,560.68,345.87,7.20;17,42.25,571.03,345.88,7.20;17,42.00,581.33,345.65,7.20;17,42.00,591.18,345.54,7.20;17,42.00,601.23,61.22,7.20;18,83.75,96.96,324.32,8.55;18,83.75,108.71,324.39,8.55;18,83.74,120.46,299.06,8.55;18,72.94,139.21,335.18,8.55;18,62.13,152.16,346.39,8.55;18,62.13,164.86,345.50,8.55;18,62.13,178.31,345.32,8.55;18,61.68,191.01,346.48,8.55;18,61.87,204.01,345.52,8.55;18,62.62,216.71,345.96,8.55;18,62.62,229.66,345.91,8.55;18,62.37,242.41,345.66,8.55;18,62.12,255.61,346.21,8.55;18,62.37,268.56,345.67,8.55;18,62.37,281.51,346.05,8.55;18,62.62,294.46,345.21,8.55;18,62.37,307.21,345.97,8.55;18,62.37,319.91,347.60,8.55;18,62.12,333.36,345.39,8.55;18,77.02,361.48,331.57,7.20;18,62.37,371.83,346.06,7.20;18,62.62,382.38,345.74,7.20;18,62.62,392.68,345.45,7.20;18,62.37,403.23,13.70,7.20"><head>64 N ote too a similar tripartite division o f the spirits in Albert's D e an im alibu s 20 . 1 . 7 . 41 (O n A nim als, 1381 ). The description Burnett provides o f the ascent o f the animal spirit to the brain is repeated by William o f Conches,"Cum igitur cerebrum eucraticum optime sit ordinatum, uno modo ad actiones virtutis animalis, alio modo respectu operationum virtutis naturalis, et nobilior sit operatic virtutis animalis, quam naturalis virtutis, nobilius erit cerebrum quod est eucraticum ad operationes animales quam ad operationes naturales; ergo perfectissimi et nobilissim i corporis cerebrum debet esse calidum et siccum. Cum igitur corpus Dominae nostrae fuerit perfectissimum secun­ dum omnia membra, ipsa habuit cerebrum calidum et siccum . . ." (Ps.-Albert, M a ria le 20. 3 , ed. Borgnet, 47 ). receive [impressions] easily but to retain them poorly. For moisture is easily changeable {mobile) and this is why women are inconstant and always seeking after som ething new. . . . Therefore there is no faithfulness in a woman. 67 T he co n clu sio n th at "there is no faith fu ln ess in a w om an" is p articu larly inappropriate fo r M ary's character and one sh ould n ot b e surprised, then, that M ary's co m p lexion w ill depart in m any w a y s from th e norm am ong w om en. T herefore, fo r P s.-A lb ert th e V irg in 's com p lexion tends tow ard warm th, a l­ th ou gh (a s w ill b ecom e evid en t b elow ) n o t for th e reason som e av o w , n am ely th at ch a stity ex ists natu rally in a cold com p lexion and therefore m an ifests it­ s e l f m o st clea rly-b y w a y o f contrast-in a w arm com p lexion . 68 R ather, it seem s, it is b eca u se our author h opes to d isa sso c ia te M ary from som e, b ut n ot a ll, o f th e con seq u en ces stem m ing from a w om an 's ty p ica l com p lexion , w h ich g en era lly w a s understood to b e phlegm atic and therefore "cold er" and "m oister" in nature th an a m an's . 69 From th e standpoint o f p h y sio lo g y , th is co m p lex io n a l co ld n ess a cts to dim inish th e b rain 's cogn itive a b ilitie s. T he co ld n ess govern in g th eir p ost-lap sarian nature a lso m akes w om en unab le to com p lete th e d igestion o f b lood , resultin g in th e n e c e ssity to purge th e body o f its co a rse and u nd igested b lood v ia m enstruation. M en, n aturally "h otter," 70 fu lly p erfect th e d ig estiv e p ro cess, thereby ob viatin g th e need fo r m enstrua­ 67 "... femina minus est habilis ad mores quam mas. Complexio enim feminae magis est humida quam m ans, sed humidi est de facili recipere et male retinere. Humidum est enim de facili mobile, et ideo mulieres sunt inconstantes et nova semper p eten tes.. . . Unde nulla tides est in muliere" (Albert the Great, Q u aestion es su p e r d e an im alibu s 15 . 11 , ed. Filthaut, 2</head><label>642017411381347676869706715112</label><figDesc>D ragm aticon 6.16.1. 65 Michael Scot, L ib e rp h isio n o m ia e 32. 66</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22" coords="18,191.09,476.23,216.91,7.20;18,61.85,486.78,346.34,7.20;18,62.10,497.33,346.34,7.20;18,62.10,507.88,346.04,7.20;18,62.35,518.23,346.16,7.20;18,62.10,528.78,346.17,7.20;18,62.35,539.08,345.06,7.20;18,61.85,549.63,342.05,7.20;18,76.75,559.73,331.22,7.20;18,63.06,570.03,218.23,7.20;18,76.76,580.38,330.87,7.20;18,62.10,590.42,345.48,7.20;18,62.35,600.52,345.53,7.20;18,62.10,610.62,325.56,7.20;19,40.55,89.26,346.37,8.55;19,40.80,102.01,346.29,8.55;19,41.30,114.71,346.28,8.55;19,41.50,127.91,345.15,8.55;19,41.05,140.86,345.36,8.55;19,41.50,153.81,345.69,8.55;19,41.50,166.31,345.62,8.55;19,41.50,179.26,248.71,8.55;19,52.30,192.01,334.58,8.55;19,41.50,205.21,345.43,8.55;19,41.50,218.16,345.08,8.55;19,41.75,231.11,345.29,8.55;19,41.50,243.81,345.71,8.55;19,41.30,256.81,346.06,8.55;19,41.50,269.76,345.77,8.55;19,42.00,282.71,346.08,8.55;19,42.00,295.66,344.85,8.55;19,41.50,308.41,346.10,8.55;19,41.50,321.36,345.38,8.55;19,41.75,334.06,345.88,8.55;19,42.00,347.26,345.90,8.55;19,41.75,360.46,345.53,8.55;19,42.00,373.21,346.09,8.55;19,42.00,386.41,345.37,8.55;19,41.50,399.10,346.36,8.55;19,41.75,412.05,346.17,8.55;19,56.40,436.13,332.06,7.20;19,41.75,446.68,345.85,7.20;19,41.75,457.03,346.41,7.20;19,42.25,467.08,344.95,7.20;19,41.75,477.63,345.65,7.20;19,42.00,488.43,57.74,7.20;19,56.40,498.53,330.56,7.20;19,40.79,509.08,59.11,7.20;19,56.39,519.43,331.46,7.20;19,41.74,529.73,187.65,7.20;19,56.39,540.03,111.30,7.20;19,56.39,550.38,330.88,7.20;19,41.74,560.68,345.82,7.20;19,41.49,571.03,346.07,7.20;19,41.49,581.33,346.01,7.20;19,41.49,591.62,345.69,7.20;19,41.49,601.72,13.75,7.20;20,63.35,98.16,346.22,8.55;20,63.10,110.43,324.73,9.45;20,73.90,123.81,334.72,8.55;20,62.65,137.01,346.32,8.55;20,63.10,150.01,345.66,8.55;20,62.90,162.96,346.89,8.55;20,62.90,174.98,345.78,9.45;20,62.90,188.41,346.78,8.55;20,63.35,200.86,346.77,8.55;20,63.60,213.38,345.73,9.45;20,63.60,227.01,251.78,8.55;20,85.45,245.01,324.22,8.55;20,85.45,257.01,324.04,8.55;20,85.45,268.81,324.30,8.55;20,85.20,280.13,324.91,9.45;20,84.94,292.81,324.32,8.55;20,85.19,304.81,324.58,8.55;20,85.19,316.56,324.66,8.55;20,85.44,328.56,324.45,8.55;20,85.19,340.31,100.25,8.55;20,74.64,359.26,335.12,8.55;20,63.35,372.46,346.44,8.55;20,63.35,384.52,346.37,9.45;20,63.59,398.16,345.86,8.55;20,63.59,411.36,345.86,8.55;20,63.58,423.62,346.07,9.45;20,78.23,455.83,331.11,7.20;20,64.28,466.13,47.76,7.20;20,77.98,476.43,331.74,7.20;20,64.08,486.78,344.74,7.20;20,63.33,497.33,345.33,7.20;20,63.58,507.88,345.24,7.20;20,63.32,518.23,346.17,7.20;20,63.32,528.78,345.91,7.20;20,63.32,539.08,126.67,7.20;20,77.97,549.63,331.74,7.20;20,63.32,559.73,345.94,7.20;20,63.32,570.03,346.18,7.20;20,63.32,580.38,345.92,7.20;20,63.07,590.68,346.04,7.20;20,62.87,600.78,346.10,7.20;20,63.32,610.83,90.90,7.20;21,41.75,88.83,345.90,9.45;21,42.00,101.78,345.80,9.45;21,42.00,115.21,346.09,8.55;21,41.50,128.16,346.19,8.55;21,41.75,141.11,155.03,8.55;21,63.85,158.18,324.40,9.45;21,63.34,170.86,324.81,8.55;21,63.59,182.61,324.46,8.55;21,63.34,194.61,324.63,8.55;21,63.59,205.73,324.77,9.45;21,63.84,218.61,235.08,8.55;21,53.04,236.68,334.30,9.45;21,42.49,250.06,345.29,8.55;21,42.24,263.01,345.33,8.55;21,42.49,276.01,345.48,8.55;21,42.70,289.21,345.96,8.55;21,42.70,301.91,345.70,8.55;21,41.75,314.61,346.49,8.55;22,60.95,97.21,346.20,8.55;22,60.50,109.91,346.74,8.55;22,61.21,122.61,345.36,8.55;22,60.96,135.36,345.62,8.55;22,60.96,148.31,14.28,8.55"><head>. Ps.-Albert's response suggests an important caveat for the theological application o f the science o f physiognomy: such a science leads to certainty only with respect to nature, and not nature ennobled by grace. Earlier in the thirteenth century Roger Bacon had made the same point: "multum debet esse prudens et expertus qui de his debet judi- care, nec de Christianis debet aliquis judicare nisi aptitudinem naturalem ad mores, non quod talis erit, quia gracia D ei gratum faciens potest vincere malam disposicionem animi ad quam excitatur ex complexione et composicione corporis .... 70 See Albert the Great, Q u aestion es su p er d e an im alibu s 5 . 10 , ed. Filthaut, 159 . 75 - 77 : "universaliter vir calidioris complexionis est quam mulier. . . ." See also Constantine the Afri­ can: "In omnibus animalibus calidiores et sicciores sunt masculi quam femme, femine frigidiores et humidiores" {L ' A rte universale d e lla m edicina (Pantegni), chap. 22 , p. 69 ). tio n , w h ich w a s p erceived to b e a sp ecia l "cu rse" or punishm ent v isite d upon th e daughters o f E ve. 71 P h y sio lo g y cannot b e separated from a con sideration o f th e p a ssio n s, h ow ever. W hen in a w om an th ese b o d ily su p erflu ities are n ot ad eq uately purged b y m enstruation, or w hen th ey are retained during p reg­ n ancy, th is o ften resu lts in a 'w arm ing' accom panied b y inordinate sex u a l de­ sire. 72 T y p ic a lly , D a n ielle Jacquart n o tes, th is relatively w arm er fem ale co m p lex io n w a s a sso cia ted w ith th e courtesan or p rostitu te (su g g estin g again a relationsh ip b etw een ch a stity and a co ld com p lexion ). 73 D e sp ite num erous argum ents, then, to su g g est that b y nature alo n e or from a com bin ation o f nature and grace th e V irgin 's com p lexion sh ould b e cold , our te x t con clu d es th at th is is n ot so . B u t, th is co n clu sio n d oes n ot fo llo w from th e p rin cip le articulated at M ariale 1 8 . 1 0 , th at th e g lo ry o f v icto ry is greater in proportion to v icto r y 's d ifficu lty ("u b i autem e st d iffic ilio r victoria, m ajor g lo ria "), su g g estin g , then, th at her v icto ry over th e p a ssio n s w ill b e m ade m ore evid en t i f sh e p o sse sse s b y nature a tem p erately w arm com p lexion (slig h tly "h o t-b lood ed ," i f you w ill, relative to other w om en ). 74 O ur author d oes n o t a ccep t th e p rem ise th at M ary's ch a stity stem s from a cold er com ­ p lex io n ; rather, in her ch astity is w h o lly a prod uct o f grace. A ccord in g to P s .- A lb ert, d esp ite th e w arm th o f her nature M ary, fu ll o f grace, n ever exp eri­ en ced co n cu p iscen ce or desire; in her even th e traces o f sin \fomes\ had b een ex tin g u ish ed . 75 In M ary there w a s n o real co n flict b etw een her p a ssio n s and her co m p lex io n a l nature; sh e w a s m iracu lou sly w ith ou t th e in clin ation to sin -to sex u a l intercourse-often a sso cia ted w ith w om en h avin g a w arm er com p lexion . T he exam ple o f her ch astity even banish ed con cu p iscen ce from th e hearts o f others-perhaps recallin g a claim fou n d in Jacobus de V o ra g in e's Golden Legend that "d esp ite M ary's exceed in g b eau ty n o m an 71 Charles T. Wood has shown that thirteenth-century theologians-especially defenders o f the Immaculate Conception-were sometimes led to a dilemma, brought on by a desire to free Mary o f the "curse" o f menstruation, w hile acknowledging that she m u st have menstruated if she were to provide the appropriate material for the birth o f the God-Man; see his "The D oc­ tor's Dilemma: Sin, Salvation, and the Menstrual Cycle in M edieval Thought,". 75 "Quod autem objicitur, quod debuit esse frigidae complexionis et habere colorem illi attestantem. Dicimus, quod non: cum enim gratia nobilior sit quam natura, castitas quae est totaliter a gratia, nobilior est quam ea quae est partim a gratia et partim a natura. Et tanto est major gratia et majorem potentiam demonstrat, quanto fortiorem vincit naturam, quamvis in beata Virgine nulla fuit pugna, quia etiam fomes extinctus fuit in ea" (ibid. 20 . 3 , ed. Borgnet, 45 ). co u ld ever d esire her, fo r th e reason that th e p ow er o f her ch a stity penetrated a ll who lo o k ed upon her, and a ll lustful d esires w ere quenched in th em ." 76 7 7 Instead, it seem s th at M ary's com p lexion m u st b e som ew hat warm er, rela­ tiv e to other w om en, n ot in order better to d isp lay a v icto r y over th e p a ssio n s b ut rather to return her com p lexion to th e b alan ce appropriate to th e sp ecies. W ere sh e to d isp la y th e phlegm atic com p lexion shared gen erally b y other w om en, sh e w ou ld depart from th e overall id eal o f a h ot and m o ist com ­ p le x io n , b e st illu strated in m ales, and rem ain, as a con sequent, a d efectiv e or fla w ed m a le (mas occasionatus) .7T I em ph asize "relative to other w om en ," sin c e co m p lexion can b e exam ined accord ing to variou s m easures. In his Q uaestiones super de animalibus, A lb ert th e G reat n otes, Com plexion can be considered three ways: either according to genus (and thus every liv in g thing is said to be hot and m oist, because on account o f these life endures); or, in a second way, according to species, and thus a human is said to be hot and m oist but the ass is hot and dry, and likew ise so is the lion. In a third way, according to the individual, and this can be considered in two ways: either comparatively or absolutely. Comparatively, ju st as one woman is said to be choleric in comparison w ith another, although nevertheless a ll women are naturally phlegm atic. I f absolutely, then th is person is said to be choleric and that one sanguine. 78 C on seq uently, alth ough in general w om en are p hlegm atic (that is , cold and m o ist), M ary's com p lexion seem s to tend tow ard b alan ce and th erefore w ill b e com p aratively w arm er than th at o f other women. A s already d iscu ssed , in order to perform its m ore n ob le operation s, her brain m u st b e w arm and dry. B a la n ce rev eals it s e lf in th e qualitas o f her b od y a s w e ll.; and Madeleine Jeay, "Albert le Grand entre Aristote et Freud: La Femme est- elle un acte manqué?" in L e R acism e: M yth es e t scien ces: P o u r L eon P oliakov, ed. Maurice Ölender (Brussels, 1981 ), 129 - 39 . 78 "Complexio tripliciter potest se habere: aut secundum genus, et sic omne vivens dicitur calidum et humidum, quia per ista stat vita. Alio modo secundum speciem, et sic dicitur homo calidus et humidus et asinus calidus et siccus et leo similiter. Tertio modo secundum indi- viduum, et hoc dupliciter: aut respective aut absolute. Respective, sicut una mulier dicitur cho- lerica respecta alterius, cum tarnen omnes nataraliter phlegmaticae. Si absolute, sic dicitur iste homo cholericus et ille sanguineus" (Albert the Great, Q u aestion es su p e r d e an im alibu s 4 . 1 - 2 , ed. Filthaut, 138 . 52 - 61 ). flesh y , th e thin, a m ixture o f th ese {synthesis), or th e balan ced. In th e V irgin M ary, h ow ever, one finds th e la st ty p e, resultin g from a com p lexion al b alan ce o f th e hum ors. 79 H er skin co lo r provides additional evid en ce o f a balan ced or tem perate com p lexion . O f s ix p o ssib le skin colors (a w h ite-red com p osite, b la ck , citrine, grey , w h ite, and redfrom balance. 80 A ll o f the others occur from inequality. The first [the w hite- red com posite] is that which is most noble and best determined to the w ell- balanced body, and thus is placed by Galen81 in a temperate com plexion and is treated in a similar way by Constantine in the P a n te c h n e . 82 For this reason, we concede that it existed in the body o f the blessed Virgin. 83 T h is lead s to certain co n clu sio n s, a s w e ll, regarding hair and ey e color. A c ­ cording to C onstantine th e A frican 84 and M ichael S c o t, 85 b lack , cu rly hair is another sig n o f a drier and warm er com plexion in th e brain. Our author con ­ cludes: "th u s it is clear . . . th at th e b est com p lexion o f th e brain, as far as concerns th e anim al v irtu es, is one th at is w arm and dry. A nd b lack hair seem s to b elo n g to su ch a brain. A nd th is is w h at C onstantine sa y s in the Pantechne, m entioned a b o v e." 86 S in ce M ary had a w arm and dry brain and in every resp ect th e m o st balan ced or p erfect com p lexion , P s.-A lb ert in sists she m u st h a v e had b la ck h air. 87 R ed (or b lon d e) hair, w h ich G alen id en tifies as a sig n o f a san gu in eou s and th erefore n ob le com p lexion , our author d ism isses. Indeed, b y th e later M iddle A g es red hair had b ecom e id en tified w ith a num ­ ber</head><label>705101597577226971727381074757175203457677819811293978412138526179808283858687</label><figDesc>" (Secretum secretorum , pars 4, c. 2, ed. Robert Steele, O p era h actenus in edita R o g eri B aconi, fasc. 5 [Oxford, 1920], 166 n.3, 125b). 69 W illiam o f Conches, D ragm aticon 6.8.3; Albert the Great, D e an im alibu s 10.1.1.11, 10.1.2.20, and 18.2.5.78 {O n A nim als, 831, 835, and 1319)Speculum 56 (1981): 710-27. 72 W illiam o f Conches, D ragm aticon 6.9.2; Albert the Great, D e an im alibu s 18.2.4.72 (O n A n im als, 1316). 73 See D anielle Jacquart, "La morphologie du corps féminin selon les médicins de la fin du moyen âge," M ic ro lo g u s 1:7 d isc o rsi d e i corpi, 83. 74 Ps.-Albert, M a ria le 18.7-9G en erally, P s.- A lb ert n o tes, b o d ies m ay b e d ivided into fiv e typ es: th e exceedingly fa t, th e 76 Jacobus de Voragine, The G olden Legend, trans. W illiam Ryan, 2 vols. (Princeton, 1993), 1:149. 77 For woman as a m a s occasion atu s, see Albert the Great, D e an im alibu s 3.2.8.158 and 16.1.14.73 (O n A nim als, 422 and 1195), and Q uaestion es su p e r d e an im alibu s 15.11 (ed. Filthaut, 265.81-8 2 ). For discussion o f this notion in Albert's work, see Paul Hossfeld, A lb e r­ tu s M a g n u s ü b er d ie F rau (Bad Honnef, 1982), reprinted in T rierer th eologisch e Z eitsch rift 91 (1982): 221^10), only that one that is a mixture o f white and red, as Johannitius says, procedes</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23" coords="22,391.27,161.01,15.32,8.55;22,60.71,174.01,346.44,8.55;22,60.96,186.96,346.29,8.55;22,60.96,199.66,346.10,8.55;22,60.96,212.86,345.91,8.55;22,60.71,225.81,346.66,8.55;22,60.71,238.81,346.86,8.55;22,60.96,251.76,345.82,8.55;22,61.21,264.71,345.45,8.55;22,60.71,277.41,346.61,8.55;22,60.96,290.41,346.12,8.55;22,60.96,303.36,347.12,8.55;22,60.71,316.31,77.23,8.55;22,72.51,329.51,334.44,8.55;22,60.71,342.46,347.40,8.55;22,60.96,355.21,346.30,8.55;22,61.21,368.41,345.58,8.55;22,61.21,381.36,346.03,8.55;22,61.46,412.83,345.72,7.20;22,61.46,423.18,345.99,7.20;22,61.46,433.48,346.00,7.20;22,61.21,444.03,345.90,7.20;22,61.21,454.83,346.00,7.20;22,60.96,465.43,346.11,7.20;22,60.96,475.48,266.24,7.20;22,75.35,486.03,331.39,7.20;22,61.20,496.38,345.53,7.20;22,60.94,506.68,48.00,7.20;22,75.59,517.03,137.40,7.20;22,75.59,527.83,330.95,7.20;22,59.99,538.13,346.92,7.20;22,60.24,548.43,305.46,7.20;22,75.34,558.78,331.02,7.20;22,60.49,568.83,158.39,7.20;22,75.59,579.42,331.26,7.20;22,60.69,589.72,346.14,7.20;22,60.49,599.82,345.89,7.20;22,60.69,610.12,88.13,7.20"><head>em ­ p lo y ed in C hristian icon ograp hy to d ep ict th e enem ies o f C hrist-Jew s in gen eral, and Judas in p articu lar. 89 B la ck hair, P s.-A lb ert affirm s, is a sig n o f a h ealth y b o d y th at h as su c c e ssfu lly purged it s e lf o f th e m o st n o x io u s hum ors w h ich , in a n y even t, w ere ab sen t from V irgin M ary's b ody. In th is in stan ce, th e S o n g o f S o n g s, w h ich d escrib es the b eloved as h avin g a "head o f fin est g o ld " b ut "h airs . . . b lack a s a raven" (S o n g o f S on gs 5 : 1 1 ) is understood not a lleg o ric a lly -as w a s so com m on-b ut quite litera lly , and th erefore lends su pp ort to th e co n clu sio n s o f p hysiogn om y. Further evid en ce is drawn from th e testim o n y o f th e v e il o f V eron ica, 90 w h ich id en tifies Jesu s a s h avin g had b la ck h air and beard. T he author o f our te x t assu m es a sim ilarity b etw een m other and S on , su ch th at from th e S o n 's hair co lo r one can in fer th e co lo r o f th e m other's hair. S im ilarly, w ith resp ect to th e co lo r o f th e V irg in 's e y e s, our te x t con clu des th a t "th e co lo r in th e ey es sh ould im m ediately in d icate th e com p lexion o f th eir ow n su b ject, and th e [V irgin 's] brain h avin g already b een determ ined w ith ou t an y doubt to b e warm and dry, th e co lo r o f th e ey es w ill b e deter­ m ined to b e b la c k ." 91 A lthough Johannitius in sisted th at b lack ey es stem m ed Scot's characterization o f a warm and dry complexion in the brain: "If the brain is o f a warm and dry complexion, the hairs grow out to be very blond and short or black or curly; this person is especially wanton; for this reason his hair w ill quickly grey and grow bald; he sleeps but little at night; he is o f great wit, quick to understand and apprehend" ("Si cerebrum fuerit cali- dae et siccae complexionis capilli nascuntur flavi fortes et curti vel nigri vel crispi; homo est multum luxuriosus, et ideo cito canescit et calvescit; parum dormit in nocte et est magnum in- genii et repentini intellectus et apprehensionis," L ib e r ph isio n o m ia e 32 ). 87 "Cum igitur corpus Dominae nostrae fuerit perfectissimum secundum omnia membra, ipsa habuit cerebrum calidum et siccum et capillos nigros" (Ps.. 90 Albert acknowledges that Jesus left a facial impression on Veronica's veil also at In E vangelium L u cae 8: 44 (ed. Borgnet, 583 ). 91 "Dicimus, quod color in oculis cum immediate significet complexionemproprii subjecti, procul dubio cerebro et calido et sicco determinato, determinabitur color oculorum niger" (Ps.- Albert, M a ria le 20. 3 , ed. Borgnet, 47 ). Compare what immediately follows with Albert's con­ tention, expressed in D e</head><label>891190913287904458391347</label><figDesc>-Albert, M a ria le 20.3, ed. Borgnet, 46). 88 Ps.-Albert, L ib e r p h isio n o m ia e 59. 89 See Ruth M ellinkoff, O utcasts: S ig n s o f O therness in N orthern E uropean A r t o fth e L a te M id d le A ges, 2 vols. (Berkeley, 1993), 1:150-59; and Claudine Fabre-Vassas, The S in gu lar B ea st: Jew s, C hristians, a n d th e P ig, trans. Carol Volk (N ew York, 1997), 107-11</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24" coords="23,341.78,141.11,44.72,8.55;23,40.29,153.81,346.53,8.55;23,40.79,166.56,346.23,8.55;23,40.29,179.51,346.32,8.55;23,40.79,192.71,97.42,8.55;23,51.09,205.41,335.71,8.55;23,40.78,218.16,346.15,8.55;23,40.78,231.11,345.98,8.55;23,41.03,244.06,345.40,8.55;23,40.53,257.01,345.56,8.55;23,41.03,270.01,345.78,8.55;23,41.03,282.96,345.55,8.55;23,41.03,295.91,345.80,8.55;23,41.28,308.86,345.68,8.55;23,40.78,321.81,346.06,8.55;23,41.03,334.81,345.56,8.55;23,41.03,347.51,345.97,8.55;23,40.78,360.46,346.07,8.55"><head>th en , "the b le ssed V irg in had a m ixture o f w h ite and red in th e co lo r o f her skin; her hair and e y e s, h ow ever, w ere m oderately [temperate] b lack ju st as w e b e lie v e th at her b elo v ed Son w a s m ore h andsom ely colored w ith resp ect to [his] form than a ll th e so n s o f m en ." 92 W h at is perhaps m ost surprising in th e te x t b y P s.-A lb ert, h ow ever, is one la st argum ent, v iz . that "w ith resp ect to th eir innate com p lexion , offsp rin g are accu stom ed to b e lik e th eir parents, and v ic e versa. B u t w e see th at in m any ca se s th e race o f Jew s has b lack hair. T herefore, a lso our L ady, sin ce sh e w as th e p rogen y o f J ew s." 93 A lthough P s.-A lb ert accep ts th e prem ise th at o ff­ spring and th eir parents gen erally resem ble on e another, 94 h e does n o t clea rly endorse th is argum ent. N ev erth eless, th e argum ent rem ains a little surprising fo r tw o reasons: first, b ecau se it clearly ack n ow led ges th e p resen ce o f a stereo ty p ica l Jew ish physiogn om y; 95 and, second , b eca u se so often C hristian art o f th e later M iddle A g es attem pts to dejudaize M ary and Jesu s, sharply d istin g u ish in g th eir appearance from th e darker, m ore om inous (even S atan ic) appearance o f Jew s, 96 d esp ite a recogn ition th at M ary's Jew ish n ess-indeed th at sh e to o , and n o t on ly Joseph, w a s o f D a v id ic d escen t! 97 -w a s n ecessary</head><label>929394959697</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot">PS.-ALBERT THE GREAT ON THE PHYSIOGNOMY OF JESUS AND MARY</note>

			<note place="foot">natum ad actiones virtutis animalis, quae proprie hunt in cerebro mediante spiritu animali qui nascitur in cerebro. Et secundum hoc calidum et siccum debet esse cerebrum, quia illae duae</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. C o n c l u s io n It is clea r th at th e grow in g attention g iv en to p h ysiogn om y in sch o la stic sc ie n tific or p h ilo so p h ica l te x ts had som e interesting con seq u en ces fo r th eo lo ­ g ia n s. P ra ctical th eo lo g y required som e con sideration o f an in d ivid u al's com ­ p le x io n in a ssig n in g an appropriate p enance, inasm uch a s on e's com p lexion m igh t p red isp ose an ind ividu al to sp e c ific sin s. S p ecu lative th eo lo g y , h ow ­ ever, lik e P s.-A lb ert th e G reat's M ariale, reasoned from a "sc ie n tific " accou n t o f th e m o st p erfectly com plexion ed hum an b od y to reach seem in gly le g iti­ m ate in feren ces regarding th e appearance o f Jesus and h is m other, M ary. In on e sen se, th ese inferences w ere n ot em p irically grounded98 b u t w ere b ased on th e d octrin es o f m edical and p h ilosop h ical auth orities</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct coords="21,67.41,342.28,320.66,7.20;21,42.70,352.63,345.88,7.20;21,42.50,363.43,345.95,7.20;21,42.50,373.73,345.22,7.20;21,42.25,384.03,345.98,7.20;21,42.70,394.63,196.85,7.20" xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quod concedimus et credimus esse verum, idem de qualitate dicentes: modi enim qualitatis corporis sunt quinque, crassities nimia, camositas, extenuata macies, synthesis, et aequalitas. Pinguedo causatur ex frigiditate et humiditate, camositas ex caliditate et humiditate, extenuata macies ex caliditate et siccitate, synthesis ex frigiditate et siccitate, aequalitas ex om­ nium humorum aequali complexione, cujus aequalitas credimus corpus beatissimae Virginis exstitsse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="21,67.95,404.93,319.66,7.20;21,42.50,415.48,270.80,7.20;21,56.90,425.83,331.71,7.20;21,42.70,436.38,345.24,7.20;21,42.69,446.68,69.11,7.20" xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signa competentis craseos secundum totam habitudinem animalis [virtutis]: color quidem ex rubeo et albo commixtus, capilli vero et rubei et medicriter crispi</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Grant, 707. Michael Scot agrees. See h is L ib e r p h isio n o m ia e 24</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Galen, M</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>S ou rce B o o k in M e d ie v a l S ci­ ence. ic rotegni, II, fol. 13ra)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="21,67.90,457.23,320.82,7.20;21,42.49,467.33,345.90,7.20;21,42.49,477.88,331.26,7.20;21,57.10,488.43,331.46,7.20;21,42.70,499.03,345.92,7.20;21,42.95,509.33,345.74,7.20;21,42.70,519.63,346.23,7.20;21,42.70,529.98,158.94,7.20" xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Et solus file qui est ex rubore et albedine compositus, ut dicit Johannicius, est ab aequalitate procedens; alii vero omnes ab inaequalitate. Primus est nobilissimus et corpori eucratico determinatus, et sic a Galeno in temperata complexione positus est, et simfii modo a Constantino in Pantechne</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Si totum corpus fuerit temperatum inter album et rufum, inter humidum et calidum, tempera[men]tum significat. Si ruffum et croceum. calorem nimium. Si tantum album frigiditatem&quot; (L &apos;Arte u niversale d e lla m edicina (Pantegni), chap. 13</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Constantine remarks. Hunc igitur concedimus in corpore beatissimae Virginis existisse&quot; (Ps.-Albert, M a ria le 20.2, ed. Borgnet, 45</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="21,67.70,540.28,320.55,7.20;21,42.70,550.62,345.46,7.20;21,42.49,560.92,158.97,7.20" xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">P ili cito nascentes. et se in altum surgentes. ostendunt cerebri siccitatem. Si nimis crispi. nigri et multi, et cito decalvandi. calorem significant</title>
		<idno>chap. 10</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>et siccitatem&quot; (L &apos;Arte universale d e lla m edicin a (Pantegni</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="21,67.44,571.22,137.52,7.20;21,56.89,581.57,331.55,7.20;21,42.69,591.62,345.76,7.20;21,42.69,602.22,345.97,7.20;23,41.03,384.03,346.66,7.20;23,41.03,394.63,57.90,7.20;23,55.68,405.18,331.09,7.20;23,40.77,415.73,345.90,7.20;23,41.27,426.03,261.36,7.20;23,55.67,436.38,331.18,7.20;23,41.27,446.93,345.90,7.20;23,41.47,457.48,235.25,7.20" xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Borgnet, 47). Cf. Michael abundance o f the watery or aqueous humor in the eye, and as a result they suffer from a sort o f night blindness. 92 &quot;Et sic beata Virgo in colore cutis fu.it alba et rubea mixtim; in capillis autem et in oculis nigra temperate fuit, sicut et ejus Filium dilectum speciosissimum forma prae filiis hominum credimus fuisse coloratum</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Scot</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Et hoc est quod dicit Constantinus in P antech n e in superioribus&quot; (Ps.-Albert, M a ria le 20.3</title>
		<editor>Ps.-Albert, M a ria le 20.3</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Borgnet, 47). 93 &quot;Secundum complexionem innatam soboles solent assimilari parentibus, et e contra; sed videmus, quod genus Judaeorum ut in pluribus habet nigros capillos. ergo et Domina nostra cum fuit de progenie Judaeorum&quot; (ibid. 19.2.5, ed. Borgnet, 44</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="23,65.96,467.58,42.16,7.20;23,55.67,477.88,330.13,7.20;23,41.02,488.43,345.34,7.20;23,41.28,498.78,342.83,7.20;23,55.42,509.08,331.46,7.20;23,41.02,519.43,345.54,7.20;23,41.72,529.98,345.04,7.20;23,41.01,540.53,345.22,7.20;23,40.76,550.83,346.23,7.20;23,41.01,561.18,345.46,7.20;23,41.01,571.48,345.38,7.20" xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">could no longer see the Jews as &apos;older brothers&apos; and even sup­ pressed the Jewishness o f Jesus o f Nazareth and his mother&quot; (14). The dark-complexioned antiJewish stereotype w as certainly known to Jews themselves in the thirteenth century</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ibid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Los</forename><surname>Berkeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Angeles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">95 This is something which Sara Lipton claims is still absent from the B ib le m oralisee, made for the king o f France between 1220 and 1229. See</title>
		<editor>Franco-German Jews</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="21" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>96 In addition to Ruth MellinkofF, O u tcasts: S ig n s o f O th ern ess in N orthern E u ropean A r t o f the L a te M id d le A ges, see also Heinz Schreckenberg&apos;s The Jew in C hristian A r t</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="23,41.26,581.82,346.45,7.20;23,41.01,591.87,199.57,7.20" xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Jew ish -C h ristian D e b a te in the H igh M id d le A ges. A C ritic a l E dition o f the N izzah on Vetus</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Philadelphia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
			<biblScope unit="page">340</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="23,65.96,601.97,320.70,7.20" xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ramon Llull stated</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>our Lady [Mary] was o f the house o f David, who w as the</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
